<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bounds set to France by the Pyrenean treaty and the interest of the confederates not to accept of the offers of peace made at this time by the French King. To which are added some short reflections; shewing, how far England is concern'd in the restitution of that treaty. Together with a list of the towns and countries that the French have taken since that time.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3834A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223870</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834717</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834717</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39221</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39221)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1808:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bounds set to France by the Pyrenean treaty and the interest of the confederates not to accept of the offers of peace made at this time by the French King. To which are added some short reflections; shewing, how far England is concern'd in the restitution of that treaty. Together with a list of the towns and countries that the French have taken since that time.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 113, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Baldwin, at the Oxford-Arms in Warwick-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an initial imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France. --  Treaties, etc. Spain, 1659-11-07 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Foreign relations --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39221:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Bounds ſet to</hi> FRANCE BY THE Pyrenean Treaty; And the Intereſt of the CONFEDERATES Not to accept of the Offers of Peace Made at this Time by the FRENCH KING.</p>
            <p>To which are added Some ſhort Reflections; ſhewing, How far <hi>England</hi> is concern'd in the Reſtitution of that Treaty.</p>
            <p>Together with a Liſt of the Towns and Countries that the <hi>French</hi> have taken ſince that Time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> at the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> 1694.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39221:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39221:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:39221:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39221:3"/>
            <head>THE BOUNDS OF <hi>France, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOUR Things have contributed to render <hi>France</hi> ſo Potent and Formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable as we behold her at this day. In the firſt Place, the ill obſervance of her Word, in reference to Treaties of Peace or Truces concluded with other So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign States, and which ſhe has violated in a little time after the Exchange of the Ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations; which has been the Original of all the terrible Misfortunes that have turmoil'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39221:4"/>
               <hi>Europe</hi> for above theſe Thirty Years, and which, perhaps, will hardly end but with the Princes Reign that firſt began the fatal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Cauſe of the Grandeur of <hi>France,</hi> was the eaſineſs ſhe met with to give her Ambition its full Swinge, by puſhing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the utmoſt of their Extent her Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant Pretenſions to the Territories and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of her Neighbours, with a Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to confine 'em within no other Bounds then thoſe of all <hi>Europe,</hi> unleſs a greater Force oppoſ'd her.</p>
            <p>The third Cauſe of her Grandeur, is the Arbitrary Power, and the Soveraign Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which the Reigning Price has made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter of by degrees, by encroaching up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Liberties of the People, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parlaments. And the fourth, is the extraordinary Means ſhe makes uſe of to encreaſe her Teaſury, and the good uſe ſhe makes of it, through the good Conduct of thoſe who are entruſted with the management of it.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe Cauſes which is, The Violation of Treaties, and which we have made choice of for the Subject of this Diſcourſe; All the World knows the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to which <hi>France</hi> was reduc'd, before the Concluſion of the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace; or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend a little lower, during the King's Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. She could hardly then bring an Army of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39221:4"/>thirty thouſand Men into the Field, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind Mony proportionable to pay 'em. For proof of which, the Queen Mother has been often heard to ſay, talking Face to Face with her prime Miniſter <hi>Mazarin; Good God! where ſhall we find Men to continue the War, and Mony to ſupply ſo many preſſing Neceſſities!</hi> And a little while after, did we not ſee M. <hi>de Turenne</hi> reduc'd to melt down his Plate, and as it were ſtrip himſelf to the laſt Farthing, to keep his Army from Periſhing? So hard a thing it was to get Mony from the Court, for that many times the Chequer was quire drain'd, and utterly unable to pay the Soldiers.</p>
            <p>It may be ſaid, that the French Monarchy was ſupported then by the Cunning and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of her Miniſters, rather then by her own Forces. Witneſs what <hi>Mazarin</hi> ſaid one day to the King. Sir, ſaid he, in reſpect of the Treaſure, <hi>Your Majeſties Conqueſts in your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet, are without all Contradiction, far the greater Number, then thoſe of your Armies.</hi> In a word, the Negotiations and Alliances which were made during <hi>Mazarin</hi>'s Miniſtry, and afterwards under the Marquiſs of <hi>Louvais,</hi> contributed more to the Aggrandizing <hi>France,</hi> and extending her Limits, then the Force of her Arms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> then having extreamly ſuffer'd, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſpace of ſeveral Years that the War with <hi>Spain</hi> laſted, ſhe was reduced to a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable condition by reaſon of her Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure's
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39221:5"/>being exhauſted, and the oppreſſion of her Subjects; and it may be ſaid, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Polities of <hi>Mazarin,</hi> the King was fain to put a good Face upon a bad Matter, which is a thing frequently practiſ'd among the French. Tho' at the ſame time ſhe made a bouncing ſhew of nothing leſs then of being inclin'd to Peace, a Conduct quite oppoſite to what ſhe obſerves at this day: And yet the Proceedings of <hi>Mazarin</hi> made it plainly appear, that <hi>France</hi> had a greater Inclination to it then <hi>Spain.</hi> In a word, that Miniſter had hardly time to bid the Queen adieu; ſo earneſt he was to be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Frontiers of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But ſome will object againſt this, the Pains that <hi>Don Antonio Piemontel</hi> took at <hi>Paris,</hi> to perſwade <hi>Mazarin</hi> to hearken to the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Peace: The great number of Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences which the Cardinal had with <hi>Don Lewis de Haro;</hi> the Delays and Difficulties that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd before the Points of that Peace could be agreed to; all which things manifeſtly prove the contrary, and that <hi>France</hi> was not ſo low as I repreſent her to be. But I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that this was only a Maſter-piece of <hi>Mazarin</hi>'s fine-ſpun Politicks, who made uſe of all the Shifts and cunning Artifices imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, to incline <hi>Don Lewis,</hi> and <hi>Don Piemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel,</hi> the Spaniſh Plenipotentiaries, to grant him all thoſe Advantages which he look'd for.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:39221:5"/>
            <p>In a word, Experience ſhews us, that he was not deceiv'd, ſince the Project which he had drawn up at Court was follow'd point by point, and every way to the Advantage of <hi>France.</hi> The greateſt Fault that <hi>Spain</hi> at that time committed was, that ſhe did not make choice of a Plenipotentiary more ſharp-ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and more nimble-witted then <hi>Lewis de Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> who was mifinform'd of the Rights which the Princes had, who were moſt remarkably concern'd in that Peace. <hi>Don Lewis</hi> made a World of Overſights in that Negotiation, and had committed many more but for the Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>M. d' Aigremont,</hi> whom the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> ſent away Poſt out of <hi>Flanders</hi> to inſtruct him in many things of which he was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</p>
            <p>It was to have bin wiſh'd, that for the good and repoſe of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and for the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Intereſts of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> that <hi>Spain</hi> had been more circumſpect in an Affair of that great Importance, wherein the high Diſpute was, not only about concluding a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and laſting Peace, but the Marriage of the <hi>Infanta.</hi> And I am perſuaded that if the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had had any Idea of good Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, he would have taken juſter Meaſures then he did, ſince it was impoſſible but he muſt have foreſeen, that by that Alliance he went about to lay the foundation of the utter Ruin of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> Nor did he want any other Example then that of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39221:6"/>to teach him that the Matches of the <hi>Infanta</hi>'s of <hi>Spain,</hi> with the Kings of <hi>France</hi> had bin always fatal to the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt be acknowldg'd that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Court at that time labour'd under a moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Blindneſs, that while they were moyling at the Negotiation of Peace, and the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the <hi>Infanta,</hi> one of the two young In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Princes happening to die, there remain'd no more then the Reigning Price to ſuceed to the Crown, and he ſo young and ſo ſickly, that 'twas much queſtion'd whether he would out-live the third Year of his Age. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, the Tidings of that young Prince's death, which ought to have made the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> tremble, conſidering the Misfortunes that threatned the Kingdom, being carry'd to <hi>Don Lewis de Haro,</hi> never put ſo much as a Minutes ſtop to the Negotiation. True it is, that <hi>de Haro</hi> had a deep ſenſe of it; but <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarin,</hi> who had his Proſpects, redoubl'd his Importunities, and haſten'd more then ever the Concluſion of the Treaty.</p>
            <p>When the Kings of <hi>France</hi> had the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to make Alliances that were likely to prove fatal to 'em, and which infallibly would have prov'd the Ruin of their Dominions, what did they do to break 'em? Witneſs the Conduct that <hi>Lewis</hi> XII. obſerv'd upon the like Occaſion. He had concluded a Treaty of Confederacy with the Emperor <hi>Maximilian.</hi> The ſecond and third Article of which Treaty
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39221:6"/>imported, that the two Princes ſhould engage themſelves to ratify and confirm the Contract of Marriage concluded between <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> Son of Arch-duke <hi>Philip,</hi> and Madam <hi>Claudia</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> the moſt Chriſtian King's Daughter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> promis'd, that in caſe he died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Iſſue Male, that the Dutchies of <hi>Milan, Genoa,</hi> as alſo the Countries of <hi>Ast</hi> and <hi>Blois,</hi> and all the other Lands and Signiories of his Demeſnes ſhould be deliver'd up, after his Death, and immediately after the Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Marriage of the Duke of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> with Madam <hi>Claudia</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> into the Hands of that Princeſs his Heireſs, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy to Perpetuity, upon condition that if ſhe happen'd to have any Siſters, ſhe ſhould allow 'em a Dowry in Mony proportionable to their Birth.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of <hi>Lewis</hi> XII. after they had ſeriouſly conſider'd how diſadvantagious this Marriage was to <hi>France,</hi> and how powerful the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> was like to grow, ſet all their Engins at work to break it. To which purpoſe, by the King's conſent, there was an Aſſembly order'd to be ſummon'd, which was held in the year 1506. at <hi>Pleſſes-Les-Tours,</hi> where the King was preſent, and by a knack of Policy, as daring as well found out, they order'd underhand, a famous Doctor of the Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> to appear upon the Stage, who came and made a Speech to the King,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39221:7"/>beſeeching him in the Name of all the States of <hi>France</hi> to match the Princeſs, his Daughter, with the Duke of <hi>Valois,</hi> preſumptive Heir of the Crown.</p>
            <p>This Doctor, with ſo much Eloquence, ſet before the King, the Misfortunes that ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly threatned <hi>France,</hi> if he ſuffer'd Madam <hi>Claudia</hi> to marry <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> or any other Foreign Prince, that from that very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Match was brok'n off; and by that manner of Proceeding <hi>Lewis</hi> XII. diſingag'd himſelf from his Word and Oath; and the Treaty which was made in 1501. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by another three Years after at <hi>Blois,</hi> was declar'd null and void.</p>
            <p>There's no Queſtion to be made but that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XII. himſelf was the Perſon who order'd the Duke of <hi>Valois</hi> to be nominated to him by all the States of the Kingdom, to the end that by that means he might bring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf off fairly from his Agreements with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximilian</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> his Son, who had reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon the word of that Prince, as upon a thing that was irrevocable.</p>
            <p>This is an Example paſt all Contradiction, beſides a great number of others that might be found in Hiſtory, ſufficient to juſtifie the Reaſons which the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> had then, has ſhe minded her own Intereſts, to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſ'd the Marriage of the <hi>Iufanta</hi> to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. who was a Foreign Prince, that they might have beſtow'd her upon the Emperor's Son,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39221:7"/>who was of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded her at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>However it were, <hi>Mazarin</hi> in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar acted the part of a great Politician, and not to mention other Important Services which he did the French Monarch, it may be ſaid, that tho' he had done nothing elſe during the whole courſe of his Miniſtry, this alone was a thing that never ought to be forgot by <hi>France.</hi> So that he made no ſcruple, to write to Monſieur <hi>le Tellier,</hi> immediately after the ſigning of the Treaty, <q>That there was great Reaſon to hope a long continuation of the Treaty, in regard that both Parties were equally ſatisfy'd. But that in his Opinion, the King had reaſon to be more contented, becauſe that all the advantage was on his ſide: And, beſides, that there was alſo this farther Benefit, that <hi>Don Lewis,</hi> believing he had don his Buſineſs admirably well, would never dream of laying hold upon Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities for the furture, ſhould they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves, to repair the great Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that <hi>Spain</hi> had receiv'd by the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that Peace.</q>
            </p>
            <p>However, had <hi>France</hi> ſtook to this Treaty, how diſadvantagious ſoever it was for <hi>Spain,</hi> and had not tranſgreſs'd the Limits that were preſcrib'd him, we ſhould not have now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held all <hi>Eurpoe</hi> in Arms, and the Princes of the Auguſt League unanimouſly reſolv'd not to ſurceaſe the War, till <hi>France</hi> has reſtor'd to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39221:8"/>every one what ſhe has wreſted from 'em ſince the Concluſion of that Treaty. Her want of Faith and Sincerity not only tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported her to declare her ſelf the Irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Enemy of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> by vertue of thoſe Rights which ſhe pretends to claim as yielded up to her by vertue of that Peace, but has openly invaded the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of other Sovereigns of <hi>Europe;</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other Right and Title, then the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges of her Ambition and Power, ſhe has run her ſelf into thoſe Exceſſes, that now make her lookt upon with Deteſtation and Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency.</p>
            <p>We have ſhew'd ye the Fault, never to be repair'd, that the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> committed in conſenting to the Marriage of the <hi>Infanta</hi> with <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and to a Treaty of Peace ſo diſadvantagious to her Intereſts. Now let us ſee the fatal Event that attended 'em, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the Bounds that were preſcrib'd to <hi>France</hi> by the Treaty; which done we will examin the Conduct which ſhe obſerv'd, to extend thoſe Limits as far as we ſee 'em now extended: And, laſtly, we ſhall conclude with repreſenting to the Princes of the League, the neceſſity of being inexorable to the Importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of <hi>France</hi> for Peace, unleſs extreamly to their Advantage: Their Intereſt to keep inviolably united together, and never to liſten to the Propoſals of <hi>France,</hi> unleſs ſhe makes Reſtitution of all that ſhe has uſurp'd ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:39221:8"/>
            <p>All the World knows, that the main thing that obſtructed the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, was the Accommodation of the Prince of <hi>Conde.</hi> We ſhall not, therefore, trouble our ſelves to recite all the Particulars that paſs'd in the great number of Conferences between the Miniſters of the two Crowns upon this Subject, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwhere to be met with. 'Tis ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſay, that <hi>Mazarin</hi> had the Honour of the Triumph, and that he obtain'd of <hi>Don Lewis</hi> all that he could expect. So true it is, that the Right and Juſtice of a good Cauſe are not battry proof againſt the Artifices of a Crafty Miniſter, and that Honeſty and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity frequently become the Cullies of wily Cunning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Lewis</hi> demanded, that the Prince in conſideration of the Services which he had done <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhould be reſtor'd to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Employments which he poſſeſs'd before his diſgrace, and that the King ſhould ſecure the Enjoyment of 'em to him and his Son the Duke of <hi>Enguien.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mazarin,</hi> who was the Prince's Irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Enemy, neatly eluded all that <hi>Don Lewis</hi> could advance to ſupport his Pret enſions, and told him in a word, that it would be a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs loſs of Time to make many Diſputes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a thing, which the King, his Maſter, would never conſent to. That the Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prince to his Governments and Employments, was enough to open a wide
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39221:9"/>Gate for Rebellion, and to encourage the great Lords of <hi>France</hi> to take up Arms againſt their Sovereign, and take part with her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies upon the leaſt diſcontent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mazarin</hi>'s unſhaken Conſtancy in this Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, quite diſarm'd <hi>Don Lewis,</hi> and was the reaſon, that at length he granted <hi>France</hi> the two Important Places of <hi>Avennes</hi> and <hi>Juliers,</hi> to obtain the Prince's Reſtoration. So that had not <hi>Mazarin</hi> bin afriad of ſome unlucky Diſappointment, as well on the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s part, who might alter his Reſolution, and refuſe his conſent to the <hi>Infanta</hi>'s Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; as on the Chriſtian Kings ſide, who was become paſſionately in love with his Niece, to whom he had made Promiſes of Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: Theſe Conſiderations, I ſay, made him preſs on the Negotiation, or otherwiſe 'tis moſt certain that <hi>Mazarin</hi> had alſo obtain'd the City of <hi>Cambray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, that in the firſt Conferences <hi>Don Lewis</hi> had propoſ'd to the Cardinal to make an Exchange of <hi>Bethune</hi> and <hi>St. Venant,</hi> for ſome other Places which he offer'd to give him, upon condition he would conſent to let 'em go. <hi>Mazarin</hi> enlarg'd himſelf at firſt very cunningly upon the Difficulties of accepting an exchange of two ſuch Poſts, ſo important and uſefull to <hi>France;</hi> however, if <hi>Don Lewis</hi> would part with the City of <hi>Cambray,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Cambreſis,</hi> he hop'd he might be able to perſuade the King not only to deliver up
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39221:9"/>
               <hi>Bethune</hi> and <hi>St. Venant,</hi> but alſo <hi>bergues</hi> and <hi>Baſſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Lewis,</hi> having conſider'd with himſelf, that the loſs of <hi>Cambray</hi> would be a great diſadvantage to <hi>Spain,</hi> and that thereby the whole Low Countries would be expoſ'd to the Invaſions of <hi>France</hi> upon the firſt Rupture, return'd for Anſwer to the Cardinal, that he would never conſent to the exchange of a Fortreſs ſo conſiderable.</p>
            <p>In the mean time Cardinal <hi>Mazarin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well ſatisfi'd with <hi>Avennes</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers,</hi> thought he had gain'd ſufficient, to make amends for his miſſing <hi>Cambray.</hi> Which made him ſay one day, as he was talking to <hi>M. de Lionne,</hi> that if he could but perſuade <hi>Spain</hi> to deliver up <hi>Juliers</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> t'would be a great ſatisfaction to him, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing convinc'd that it would be more for the Honour of <hi>France,</hi> then the winning of four good Towns.</p>
            <p>So that he made no ſcruple of writing to the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> 
               <q>That he had not only got <hi>Avennes,</hi> which his Royal Highneſs deem'd ſo important, but alſo the Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Juliers</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> with other Advantages, which had coſt the King no more then the Government of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy</hi> for the Prince, and the Employment of <hi>Grand Maiſtre</hi> for the Duke of <hi>Anguien</hi> his Son.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:39221:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Avennes,</hi> as all the World knows, is a Place of Importance in the Low Countries within the Province of <hi>Hainault,</hi> between the <hi>Sambre</hi> and the <hi>Meuſe.</hi> It bears the Title of an Earldom, and lies not above four Leagues from <hi>Landrecy,</hi> and as many from <hi>Maubeuge:</hi> And this Town was in part the Boundary that was allotted to <hi>France</hi> on that ſide: And by the yielding up of that City, the particular Intereſts of the Prince of <hi>Chimai,</hi> were ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic'd to the Publick. Now let us view the reſt of the Boundaries.</p>
            <p>By the XXXV. Article of the Treaty it was concluded, That the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhould remain ſeiz'd of, and effectually enjoy the following Places, <hi>viz. Arras</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Artois, Heſden, Bapaume, Bethune, Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, Lens</hi> in the County of <hi>St. Pol, Terroane, Renti,</hi> as alſo all the other Bailliages and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellan-ſhips of the ſaid <hi>Artois;</hi> except only <hi>Aire</hi> and <hi>St. Omer,</hi> with their Appurtenances and Annexes.</p>
            <p>By the XXXVI. Article it was agreed, That in the Province of <hi>Flanders,</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhould be poſſeſs'd of <hi>Graveline,</hi> the Forts <hi>Philip, Ecluſe, Hannuin, Bourbourg</hi> and <hi>St. Venant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the XXXVII. is was concluded, That in the Province and County of <hi>Hainault,</hi> the moſt Chriſtian King ſhould enjoy <hi>Landre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci</hi> and <hi>Queſnoi.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:39221:10"/>
            <p>By the XXXVIII. Article it was likewiſe greed, That the moſt Chriſtian King ſhould enjoy in the Dutchy of <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> the ſtrong Holds of <hi>Thionville, Montmedi</hi> and <hi>Damvilliers;</hi> the Provoſtſhip of <hi>Ivoy, Chavanci, Chateau</hi> and the Provoſtſhip belonging to it, the Town and Poſt of <hi>Marville,</hi> ſeared upon a little River called <hi>Vexin,</hi> which belong'd formerly in part to the Dukes of <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> and partly to thoſe of <hi>Barr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the XXXIX. it was agreed, That <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienburgh</hi> and <hi>Philippeville,</hi> ſeated between the <hi>Sambre</hi> and the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> with their Appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Annexes ſhould be allowed the moſt Chriſtian King, in exchange for <hi>la Baſſee</hi> and <hi>Berg St. Winox,</hi> and the Fort Royal, of which the Catholick King was to remain in Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>by the XLIV. Article it was covenanted, That the Catholick King ſhould re-enter into, and enjoy the County of <hi>Charleroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the XLV. the King of <hi>Spain</hi> engag'd to reſtore to the moſt Chriſtian King, <hi>Rocroy, Chatelet</hi> and <hi>Linchamp,</hi> with their Dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Annexes.</p>
            <p>By the XLVI. Article it was agreed, That the moſt Chriſtian King ſhould reſtore to the Catholick King, the Cities and Places of <hi>Ypre, Dixmude, Oudenard, Furnes,</hi> with their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the Boundaries preſcrib'd to <hi>France</hi> in the Low Countries: We ſhall now
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39221:11"/>ſet down the Bounds that were aſſign'd her in <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Negotiation began at <hi>Madrid,</hi> in the Year 1656. upon which the preſent Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was grounded, it was concluded, That the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Mountains, which had anciently divided <hi>Spain</hi> from <hi>Gaul,</hi> ſhould alſo part the two Kingdoms at this day.</p>
            <p>In purſuance of which, the moſt Chriſtian King was to remain in Poſſeſſion of all the County of <hi>Viguery</hi> of Juriſdiction of <hi>Rouſſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> of the County and Juriſdiction of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flans,</hi> and of the Countries, Cities, Places, Caſtles, Burroughs, Villages and other Places of which it conſiſts. It was alſo agreed That the County of <hi>Cerdaigne,</hi> in the Principality of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> ſhould remain in the Hands of the moſt Catholick King.</p>
            <p>By the XLIX. the moſt Chriſtian King engages to reſtore to the Catholick King, the ſtrong Holds and Ports of <hi>Roſes, Trinity Fort, Capa de Quers, la Seau d' <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rgel, Toxen,</hi> the Caſtle of <hi>Baſtide;</hi> the Towns and ſtrong Holds of <hi>Baga, Ripol,</hi> and the County of <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daigne,</hi> wherein are <hi>Belver, Puicerda, Carol,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Cerdaigne,</hi> in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as then it was. 'Twas alſo ſaid, That Part of <hi>Cerdaigne,</hi> that lay in the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Mountains on that ſide next <hi>France,</hi> ſhould remain to his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, as ſhould be regulated, by Umpires on both ſides.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39221:11"/>
            <p>The Boundaries allotted to <hi>France</hi> on <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nany</hi> ſide were <hi>Juliers,</hi> the chief City of the Dutchy of the ſame Name, which belong'd to the Duke of <hi>Newburg,</hi> from whom it had bin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aken by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> but reſtor'd to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain by the Treaty: And ſo the Duke of <hi>Newburg</hi> being a Confederate with <hi>France,</hi> that Place was at her Diſpoſal; and as ſuch, we ſhall look upon it as one of the Barriers that were aſſign'd her on that ſide. As for <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the moſt Catholick King conſented by the LXII. Article, that it ſhould be reſtor'd to her Lawful Sovereign, upon condition that the Duke ſhould demoliſh the Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Nanci;</hi> never to be repair'd any more. He conſented alſo, that the fore-mention'd Duke ſhould be reſettl'd in the Cities, Places and Countries which he formerly poſſeſs'd, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon the three Biſhopricks of <hi>Metz, Toul</hi> and <hi>Verdun,</hi> except <hi>Moyenvic,</hi> ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to <hi>France</hi> by the Treaty of <hi>Munſter,</hi> in 1648. excepting alſo the County of <hi>Clermont,</hi> and the Demeſnes belonging to it, and the Fortreſſes, Provoſtſhips and Territories of <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai, Dun</hi> and <hi>Jamets,</hi> with their Revenues; which Places, together with the Dutchy of <hi>Barr,</hi> were to remain united to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>Alſatia</hi> ſide it was agreed by the LXVII. Article, That his Catholick Majeſty ſhould, by the Treaty, renounce all Rights and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions which he had or might have hereafter
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39221:12"/>to the upper and lower <hi>Alſatia,</hi> the <hi>Zuntga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the County of <hi>Ferrette, Briſac</hi> and its Depe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> dencies; as alſo to all the Countries, Placer Rights and Claims that were ſurrenderd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty by the Treaty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Munſter, Octob.</hi> 4. 1648. to be united and in corporated into the Crown of <hi>France:</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Catholick Majeſty approving, by vertue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſaid Renunciation, the Contents of the ſaid Treaty: In lieu of which Renunciation his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty engages to make juſt payment of the three Millions of Livers which he was oblig'd by the ſaid Treaty to pay the Archdukes of <hi>Inſpruch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the County of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the XLVIII. Article, That the moſt Chriſtian King ſhould reſtore to the Catholick King, the Fortreſſes of St. <hi>Amour, Bleterans Toux</hi> and their Dependences, together with all the Fortifi'd Poſts poſſeſs'd by the Arms o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty within the ſaid County, without reſerving or detaining any thing to himſelf.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Italy,</hi> it was covenanted by the XLVIII. Article, That the moſt Chriſtian King ſhould reſtore to the Catholick King the Fortreſſes of <hi>Valence</hi> upon the <hi>Po,</hi> and <hi>Mortara</hi> with their Dependences. On the part of <hi>Spain, Vercueil</hi> was to be reſtor'd to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Confederate.</p>
            <p>For Brevity's ſake, we ſhall content out ſelves, with allowing on <hi>Italy</hi>-ſide for the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39221:12"/>French Limits, the Important Place of <hi>Pigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rol,</hi> which we may number among the Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Acquiſitions of the King of <hi>France</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Reign; and wherein Negotiation and Artifice had a greater ſhare then the pretended Claims which he has always boaſted. Such are the Cities of <hi>Dunkirk, Caſal</hi> and <hi>Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> of which more at large in the ſequel of our Diſcourſe. It will be ſufficient at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſay, That the moſt Chriſtian King made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Pignerol</hi> by vertue of a particular Treaty made with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> by which that Prince deliver'd to him that Fortreſs, and had in recompence ſome certain Territories in <hi>Montferrat,</hi> for which his Majeſty promis'd to pay the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> the Sum of Fourteen Millions in Gold. Thus <hi>France</hi> has kept in ever ſince. And by means of that Fortreſs, has ſecur'd her Frontiers on that ſide, and has preſerv'd a Paſſage open to fall into <hi>Piedmont</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> when ſhe pleaſes, and carry her Arms into the Heart of the Territories of the <hi>Italian</hi> Princes. By the Surrender of that Place, the Dukes of <hi>Savoy</hi> deſpoyl'd themſelves of the ancient Liberty which they formerly enjoy'd and are become Salves and Victims to the moſt Chriſtian King.</p>
            <p>Thus in a few Words, we have ſet down the Limits that were aſſign'd to <hi>France</hi> by the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, and, as I may ſo ſay, the moſt eſſential part of that famous Negotiation.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39221:13"/>I might add to all theſe Advantages which t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> moſt Chriſtian King receiv'd the particular Intereſts of the Princes ally'd to <hi>Spain,</hi> which <hi>Don Lewis</hi> ſacrific'd with ſo much Impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Cruelty, only to improve and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Intereſts of the Prince of <hi>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which vex'd the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to ſee himſelf deſpoyl'd of half his Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by a Treaty. Who, thereupon, arrivin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Poſt at the Place where the Conferences were held, his Reſentment tranſported him to that degree, that he told <hi>Don Lewis</hi> to his Fact 'Twas a ſhame to ſee with what Ingratitude the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> repaid the great Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which he had done it for about eight an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> twenty Years together. <hi>That, in ſhort, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be ſo ſtripp'd of his Territories; there re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> main'd nothing more for him to do, but to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelf to Sea, and wander on the Wave till Fortune found him out a Reſting Place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mazarin,</hi> whoſe aim it was to draw that Prince into a cloſure with <hi>France,</hi> was over joy'd to ſee him under thoſe Diſturbances, as well to mortifie him, as to renew his vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for not having laid hold of thoſe Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which the moſt Chriſtian King had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly propoſed to him, would he have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd her Intereſts, and abandon'd the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed <hi>France</hi> offer'd to reſtore the beſt part of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and all his Territories; as alſo to lend him Forces, in order to Beſiege
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39221:13"/>
               <hi>Clermont</hi> and <hi>Stenay,</hi> in the peaceable Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which he ſhould have remain'd: To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve given him <hi>Mogenvic,</hi> which was at his Majeſties Diſpoſal: And beſides all thoſe great advantages, the King promis'd to look upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m as a Prince, to whom he ſhould have been beholding, for having aſſiſted him at a time then the Civil Wars afflicted <hi>France.</hi> But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> too much addicted t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſlighted all theſe Offers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſwading himſelf that the King of <hi>France</hi> would make him pay dearly for 'em, if he would accept 'em.</p>
            <p>The Unfortunate Prince then finding that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e had no time to loſe, becauſe the Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries were juſt ready to Sign, offer'd <hi>Mazarin</hi> as his laſt Remedy, to perſwade Don <hi>Lewis</hi> to allow <hi>France</hi> a conſiderable Thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are into <hi>Alſatia</hi> through <hi>Franche Conte,</hi> with all the Towns and Cities that lay upon that Paſſage, provided the King would releaſe to him the Dutchy of <hi>Barr;</hi> which was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable a thing ſaid he, that he would give the Cardinal his Oath, that it never yielded him 4000 Livers a Year. But the two Plenipotentiaries met with ſo many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties to agree upon Expedients to the Duke's Content, that <hi>Mazarin</hi> carried it in this, as he had done in all other things. Beſides that, he was deſirous to reſerve for the King his Maſter the Honour of doing the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> a Kindneſs, as he had done in reference to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39221:14"/>Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> to the end he might bind both the one and the other ſo much the faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to his Intereſts; and becauſe it ſhould n'er be ſaid, that <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould one day boaſt to have inforc'd <hi>France</hi> to make Reſtitution of what belong'd to thoſe Princes, at the Peril of his Majeſties Clemency, who reſerv'd the Honour of it wholly to himſelf.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Spain</hi> took little care of the Intereſts of her Confederates, <hi>France</hi> took a quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Courſe in reſpect of <hi>Portugal,</hi> the Dukes of <hi>Newburg, Savoy</hi> and <hi>Modena,</hi> her Allies; for whom the Cardinal procur'd all the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages they could expect. What an Honour was it for <hi>France,</hi> what a Happineſs at the ſame time for the Duke of <hi>Newburg!</hi> He did but enter into an Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> and preſently had his Territories reſtor'd him <hi>France</hi> quits all, abandons a part of her own Intereſts, and cauſes Reſtitution to be made of the City of <hi>Juliers,</hi> to the prejudice of the Emperor's and the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh's</hi> Claims: While on the Part of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſuch Soveraign Princes as the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who had ſerv'd her above Eight and twenty Years, are depriv'd of all.</p>
            <p>In truth, moſt Serene Princes, who are at this day united in Confederacy againſt <hi>France,</hi> as I cannot but reflect upon a Conduct ſo little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the Juſtice of a potent Monarchy, ſo I cannot but humbly lay befnre you this Noble <hi>Memento.</hi> That being upon the point of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39221:14"/>a Peace with the Moſt Chriſtian King, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtands with your Honour to take a care, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at it be not a Peace like the reſt, and that one of the Princes comprehended in this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt Confederacy, wherein you have ſo juſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rm'd your ſelves, may have the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to charge you with the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</p>
            <p>Methinks I hear <hi>France</hi> already loudly giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, as ſhe did in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Francis</hi> I That the Protecting of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> was never capable of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng the Princes that ſided with her from Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. Witneſs, ſay they, what at that me befell the Dukes of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and what has befallen Duke <hi>Victor Amedeas</hi> II. Which man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Arguing makes me judge that <hi>France</hi> as a ſtrong Confidence in the Engine ſhe is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tting at work to bring him off from the confederacy, ſhe fails not to Peal in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ars, that he is upon the brink of being For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the reſt of the Princes, as his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>himai</hi> were formerly; and as an accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Misfortune, of ſeeing his unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Dominions become the Innocent Victim of he Common-Cauſe, which freequently Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices the Weakeſt.</p>
            <p>But let ut return to our Subject: And now behold all <hi>Europe</hi> wiſtfully expecting to enjoy he Sweets of a ſolid and durable Peace, after which ſhe has panted ſo many Years. <hi>Spain</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:39221:15"/>is the firſt that has reaſon to conceive great Hopes from ſo August a Treaty, and an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance that one would think ſhould revive the Amity that flouriſh'd betwen the two Houſe in the Reigns of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> XII Thoſe two Princes in teſtimony of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended conſtant Union, and inviolable Friend ſhip, would needs that the firſt Article of the Treaty of <hi>Blois,</hi> ſhould be expreſſ'd in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Words, <hi>The Moſt Chriſtian King, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick King ſhall be as two Souls in one an the ſame Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would to God we had as much reaſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ſide to continue the ſame Language, and that we had not rather cauſe to ſay of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. what the Hiſtorian ſaid of the <hi>Dauphin</hi> who fled for Succour to the Court <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Burgundy;</hi> that upon the Marriage of the Monarch with the Infanta of <hi>Spain,</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Altecration, Diſcord, Brandling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Devils entred with him into the Houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Austria.</hi> 'Tis alſo obſervable, that the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when that unhappy Alliance was conclude was ſo Tempeſtuous and ſo outrageouſly Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my, that the Plenipotentiaries were at a lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whether they ſhould ſtay or run out of the Room, ſo great the Danger was that threatn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 'em. It ſeem'd as if Heaven had had a de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſign to have hinder'd the concluſion of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract that was made on purpoſe to ſow the Seeds of thoſe Diſmal Confuſions and Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that afterwards o'erwhelm'd all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:39221:15"/>
            <p>And thus we have ſeen the Bounds that were preſcrib'd to <hi>France</hi> by the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty. Now let us ſee how far either her Ambition or her breach of Faith extended 'em and the Springs that ſhe ſet at work to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade the Poſſeſſions of her Neighbours, and to Cloath her ſelf with the Spoils of ſo many Oppreſſed Princes whom ſhe Sacrificed to her Avarice to form the Powerful Monarchy that ſo long has been the Terror of <hi>Europe.</hi> Modern Hiſtorians have great reaſon to ſay, That <hi>France</hi> is now no longer to be found in <hi>France,</hi> ſhe is become ſo much alter'd and out of Knowledge. How many States, Signio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Demeſnes and Principalities has ſhe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded! What Potentate could vaunt himſelf ſecure from her impious Tyranny! I find not any in all the four Parts of the World: The whole Earth upbraids her with her Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>Let 'em not tell me, that <hi>France</hi> has ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd to that high degree of Exaltation and Power, by the Rights or Claims that have been yielded to her by virtue of Alliances, or Treaties, which have ſucceeded that of the <hi>Pyrenans.</hi> For to that I anſwer, That the Princes of the League are not to take notice of any other then the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, and that 'tis a favour done her if they ſhould not diſpute the Places with her that were allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her by that Treaty, which was brought to Perfection to the Advantage of <hi>France,</hi> by the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39221:16"/>Treachery and Cunning of <hi>Mazarin</hi> prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the Weakneſs and witleſs Inſufficiency of <hi>Don Lewis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a Truth ſo generally receiv'd that all the World knows it, That <hi>France</hi> conſtrain'd the Confederates, by force of Arms, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the two Treaties of <hi>Aix la Chapelle</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen.</hi> So that if the Duke of <hi>Venice, Andrea Gritti,</hi> call'd the City of <hi>Cambray</hi> the <hi>Venetian</hi>'s Purgatory, becauſe all the Treaties there concluded between the two Emperors and the two Kings of <hi>France,</hi> had bin fatal to the moſt Serene Republick: We may with as much reaſon call the Cities of <hi>Aix la Chappelle</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> the Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the Confederates in regard of the Injuſtice of <hi>France</hi> appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating to her ſelf, while ſhe had ſuch numerous Armies on foot, the greateſt part of their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories under pompous and chimerical Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, claims of the Queen, Right of Devolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Dependency and Covenience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, indeed, if I may preſume to ſay ſo <hi>France</hi> may be ſaid to have ſoundly purg'd both <hi>Spain</hi> and the Confederates by the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Aix la Chapelle</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> if we conſider the Loſſes which they have ſuſtain'd through the ſurrender of a great many Towns and Fortreſſes, to which the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Power conſtrain'd 'em, and to which he had no Right. God grant we may not fall into the like Misfortunes if it ſhould come to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39221:16"/>Treaty, in the management of which it will behove the Confederate Princes to make choice of able and faithful Plenipotentiaries. Let 'em remember, that if <hi>Mazarin</hi> had the Honour to carry away all the Advantages that <hi>France</hi> could expect from the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation; <hi>Colbert Croiſſi</hi> was no leſs ſucceſſful in that of <hi>Nimeguen:</hi> And that both the one and the other of thoſe Miniſters, were as cunning to improve their Intereſts, as the t'other ſide were unwary and negligent in ſuffering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſurpriz'd.</p>
            <p>After the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Peace, the firſt ſtep that <hi>France</hi> made to the extending of her Limits into <hi>Germany,</hi> was to take a fair occaſion to deſpoil the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> of his Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: And this that follows, was the ſuggeſtion of her Crafty Ambition. The King of <hi>France</hi> always made a cunning uſe of Marriages, and we ſee but very few Negotiations wherein he has not affected to employ Women; becauſe they are really inſinuating, for that the Man muſt be very obdurate, who can reſiſt the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of their Charms.</p>
            <p>The King then propoſed to the Duke (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that he would refuſe him) a Match between Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his Nephew, and a Princeſs of <hi>France.</hi> The Duke appear'd as could as Ice, as having no mind to liſten to the Propoſal, and, in ſhort, refuſed to conſent to it; perſuading himſelf that the Alliance would prove fatal to him, and be the infallible Ruin
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39221:17"/>of his Territories, and his Nephew that was to ſucceed him. <hi>France</hi> finding the firſt Hook would not take, bethought her ſelf of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Artifice. She ſet a foot Suſpitions, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſts and Menaces. Suſpitions, by repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to the Duke, that Prince <hi>Nicholas Francis</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Brother, and Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his Nephew betray'd him, and held Intelligence with the Court of <hi>France,</hi> tho' there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo falſe. Which done, perceiving the Duke would not declare himſelf, ſhe rais'd her Tone a little higher, and gave him to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that if he continued obſtinate in giving his conſent to the Marriage, ſhe would ſeize upon his Territories, and deliver 'em in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to' the Hands of his Nephew.</p>
            <p>The Duke, who had had ſufficient Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence all his Life time, what <hi>France</hi> would do if ſhe were not obey'd, thought there was no way to recoil, but that her unfortunate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny had plung'd him into an Abyſs from Whence he ſhould never be able to deliver himſelf, but by the loſs of what he had moſt dear and valuable in this World, that is to ſay, his Liberty and his Territories. So that he reſolv'd to ſtrip himſelf of his Dutchies of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Barr,</hi> with their Dependences and Annexes in favour of <hi>France,</hi> to the end that ſhe ſhould enjoy 'em after his Death, with all the Rights and Priviledges of Soveraignty and that they ſhould for ever be united and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into the Demeans of the Crown
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39221:17"/>only that he ſhould enjoy 'em during his Life.</p>
            <p>But the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who had ſhew'd ſo much Conſtancy at other times, when <hi>France</hi> ſought his Deſtruction, now imprudently fell into the Springes which ſhe ſet for him. Which made the Politicians ſay, That he had more Folly then Judgment in his Conduct. If we conſider one Circumſtance, that happen'd the very day that he ſurrender'd his Territories to <hi>France,</hi> and which is very remarkable, it muſt be agreed, that the Duke had in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner loſt his Senſes. For you muſt know, That this ſame Prince being lockt up in a Chamber, where he was left all alone for a while, and afterwards told, That he muſt never think to be let out again till he had renounc'd his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories: The Duke, who found himſelf to be a Priſoner, reſolved at length to purchaſe his Liberty at the expence of all his Signiories. To which purpoſe, he took the Pen, Ink and Paper, that was left him upon the Table, and drew up in Writing, a Draught of the Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his Dutchies to <hi>France.</hi> After he had finiſh'd the Draught, he fill'd the Margin of Reſignation with a great number of little Birds, which he drew with his Pen, and ſent the whole to be deliver'd to his Majeſty, who could not forbear Laughing, to ſee ſuch an Aviary in Paper: An undeniable Proof that the Duke knew not what he did.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:39221:18"/>
            <p>Theſe were the firſt Fruits which <hi>France</hi> reaped from the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the LXVII. and LXIX. Articles; <hi>Mazarin</hi> took care to inſert into the Articles of the Treaty, and which he needs would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to dictate himſelf. By the firſt it was agreed, That neither Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> nor any Prince of his Houſe, ſhould continue in Arms, but ſhould be oblig'd to disband his Forces upon the Publication of the Peace. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Article confirm'd, That the Duke ſhould allow a free Thorough-fare for his Majeſties Armies to march into <hi>Alſatia,</hi> to <hi>Briſac</hi> or <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> when ever the King ſhould demand it. Obſerve the depth of the Artifice. <hi>France</hi> conſents the <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſhould be reſtor'd to her Lawful Sovereign, but ſhe reſerves Paſſages and Thorough-fares to return thither when ſhe pleaſes. She conſents, That a Sovereign Prince ſhall enjoy his Liberty for the future; but, firſt, he muſt lay down his Arms; ſecondly, he muſt demoliſh the Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of his ſtrong Holds, and <hi>France</hi> muſt have the keeping of the Keys of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to the end, that when ſhe has a mind to make her ſelf Miſtreſs of 'em, ſhe may do it without meeting any Reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the Bounds of the French Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy enlarg'd of a ſudden, and extended into <hi>Germany,</hi> by the addition of all the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of a Sovereign Prince, without having any Right or Pretence to Invade 'em, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39221:18"/>they lay convenient for her: Tho' Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate <hi>Talon</hi> ſpent all the Reaſon and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he had to the laſt drop, to prove the contrary in a full Parliament; aſſerting, That <hi>Lorrain</hi> had always depended upon the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and, conſequently, that 'twas but juſt it ſhould be re-united to the Crown.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>France,</hi> conſidering the good luck that had attended him on <hi>Germany</hi> ſide, turn'd all his Deſigns toward the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, to ſee whether Fortune would preſent him with any favourable occaſion to aggran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize himſelf, and enlarge his Frontiers that way. To that purpoſe, he caſt his Eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> with a Reſolution to ſacrifice Hecatombs, ſo he might but get that Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Place out of the Hands of the Engliſh. And, indeed, the ſtrict Ties of Amity contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with King <hi>Charles,</hi> during his Exile, had decoy'd that Unfortunate Prince into an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement not to refuſe him any thing; and, knowing his weak ſide, he made him an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, underhand, of four Millions, and a fair Miſtreſs over and above the Market-price: Charms ſufficiently powerful to engage him to make ſuch a falſe Step, as render'd, and will for ever render, both him and his Memory odious to Poſterity.</p>
            <p>But the Ambition of <hi>France</hi> ſtopt not here; there was a neceſſity of giving it its full ſwinge; the Revenues and Right of the Church muſt not be ſpar'd, when the Aggran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſement
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39221:19"/>of <hi>France</hi> was the main thing in diſpute. Her Bounds were ſtill to narrow for her to be confin'd within 'em. Therefore ſhe fell upon Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VII. and ſeiz'd upon <hi>Avignon,</hi> after ſhe had enrag'd the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of that City to mutiny againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. If you ask what Ground ſhe had for her Pretenſions? She will anſwer, That the Pope did not do what he would have had done for him. Hence it came to paſs, that the order of all things was ranvers'd. The eldeſt Son of the Church takes up the Rod to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe the common Father of the Chriſtians, becauſe he proves diſobedient; whereas, 'tis generally ſeen, that Fathers correct their Children when they fail of their Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pepin,</hi> the Son of <hi>Charles Martell,</hi> the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Third King of <hi>France,</hi> of the ſecond Race, was the Glory of his Age, and the greateſt Example of Piety and Veneration towards the Popes, of any among all our Kings. His Zeal ſo eminent, when he march'd into <hi>Italy</hi> to ſuccour Pope <hi>Zachary,</hi> moſt cruelly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the <hi>Lombards;</hi> the Marks of his Friendſhip and Tenderneſs beſtow'd upon Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> III. who fled for Refuge into <hi>France;</hi> and his raiſing the Siege of <hi>Rome,</hi> which <hi>Aſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> King of the <hi>Lombards</hi> was conſtrain'd to quit, as being enforced to ſue for Peace to <hi>Pepin,</hi> who kept him cloſe block'd up; all theſe ſignal Services which he did the holy See, acquir'd him the glorious Sir-name of <hi>Moſt Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:39221:19"/>
            <p>Now if we compare King <hi>Pepin</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, with the Behaviour of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Popes, 'twill be no difficult thing to conclude, that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> never had a greater Enemy then this Prince; and, conſequently, that there is nothing which he leſs deſerves then the Sir-name of Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. If you demand a Reaſon for all theſe Extravagancies, you need no more then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult his Ambition; that Paſſion will make anſwer, That when once it got Poſſeſſion of his Heart, there was nothing in the World which it did not prompt him to undertake for the ſatisfaction of it. So that 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if the Rights of the Church, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is more Sacred and Augnſt, are become Victims to his Exorbitant Deſires.</p>
            <p>But what does <hi>France</hi> do further ſtill? She was oblig'd by one of the Articles to abandon the Protection of <hi>Portugal;</hi> promiſing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, to employ her utmoſt Induſtry to perſuade that Prince, in Friendly Terms, to compoſe the Differences which he had with <hi>Spain.</hi> But hardly were the Ratifications exchang'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe made a Laughing Stock of her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: She gave out Commiſſions underhand, and caus'd the Drums to beat up publickly at <hi>Paris,</hi> in order to the Raiſing of Souldiers for the ſervice of that Crown.</p>
            <p>But all this is nothing: Here comes another Tragical Event, that makes her Miſtreſs, all of a ſudden, of a vaſt extent of Country, of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39221:20"/>ſeveral Signiores, Dukedoms, Marquiſats and Earldoms; and becauſe that was not enough to ſatisfy her unſatiable Avarice, whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms muſt become her Victim and her Prey. I mean the Death of <hi>Philip</hi> IV. The loſs of that Prince drew Tears from the Eyes of <hi>Spain,</hi> and all <hi>Europe;</hi> but <hi>France</hi> leapt for Joy. That Ambitious Potentate finding the time was come to ſpread abroad his vaſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and extend his Limits, at the Expences of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſacrifices whatever is moſt ſacred in Religion, and in the venerable Alliance which he had contracted: Neither Honour, Oaths, Faith ſolemnly ſworn, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is capable to ſtop him.</p>
            <p>However, that he might ſtill preſerve ſome ſhadow of Juſtice, and authorize his Conduce by ſome ſhew of Reaſon, his Majeſty public ſhed a Manifeſto, wherein he ſet up the Queens claim to <hi>Brabant,</hi> and ſome other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of the Low Countries. This Right was otherwiſe called a devolved Right, by vertue of which a Brother born in the ſecond Wedlock, is excluded from the Succeſſion, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Siſter of the firſt Venter. And this is the Diſpute between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain; Charles</hi> II. being the Iſſue by the ſecond Marriage.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>France,</hi> therefore, having demanded of the Queen Regent of <hi>Spain</hi> the Dominions devolved to him in right of <hi>Mari Tereſa</hi> his Wife, he would not ſtay till the Council of <hi>Sapin</hi> return'd him an Anſwer
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39221:20"/>His Impatience to aggrandize himſelf and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his Limits, ſpurr'd him on to be before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with all the World: So that without any Declaration of War he ſeizes upon <hi>Bergue, Furnes, Tournai, Douay, Courtray, L'Iſle, Oudenard, Alost,</hi> and all the Places that lay convenient for him: And to theſe Conqueſts, he joins the Important Cities of <hi>Salins, Beſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Dole;</hi> after which follow'd the total Reduction of <hi>Franche Conpte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing could ſtop the Rapidneſs of his Arms; there was a neceſſity of altering his Bounds, and he muſt enlarge 'em to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extent of his boundleſs Ambition. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could ſtand in his way but the Triple Alliance; nothing elſe could make him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to a Treaty of Peace: By which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores back to <hi>Spain</hi> nothing but what he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes himſelf, while he keeps thoſe Places which he deems of greateſt Importance, and moſt proper to ſavour his Enterprizes. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſents to a Treaty at <hi>Aix la Chapelle,</hi> but with a mental Reſervation, as <hi>Mahonia</hi> call'd it; that is to ſay, That he promis'd <hi>Spain</hi> to lay down his Arms, provided ſhe quits to him all the Places and Towns, that he had ſeiz'd in 1667. reſerving to him ſelf a Power to begin the War agen, ſo ſoon as the Peace ſhould be concluded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spain</hi> is there enforc'd to quit <hi>Chatle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, Binch, Ath, Douay, Tournay, Oudenard, L'Iſle, Armentier, Courtray, Bergh</hi> and <hi>Furnes,</hi> with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39221:21"/>all their Dependencies, Appurtenances and Juriſdictions. One would have thought, that after ſo many Advantages <hi>France</hi> would have been ſatisfy'd, and would have let the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates and <hi>Spain</hi> have been at quiet, at leaſt, for ſome Years. But that was the leaſt of her Intention. For in 1671. her old inſatiable Paſſion rous'd her again, and ſhe that had vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace, the moſt ſolemn, the moſt ſacred, that <hi>France</hi> ever made, ſign'd by all the Nobility and Grandees of both Crowns, might with much more reaſon infringe the Treaty of <hi>Aix la Chapelle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, then, without conſulting any other then her old Miſtreſs Ambition (and, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways when that Paſſion gives the word, his Armies are ready to march, and his Generals are in a condition to put his Deſigns in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution) the firſt Step, then, that <hi>France</hi> made after the Peace of <hi>Aix la Chapelle,</hi> was her declaring War againſt <hi>Holland,</hi> after ſhe had made uſe of all the Artifices imaginable to break off the Engagement, that united 'em with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Sweden.</hi> If you demand a Reaſon for this Rupture; ſhe will anſwer, That the King had Inducements to look upon thoſe People no otherwiſe then as the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his Realm, and upon no other Grounds marches his Armies, and in leſs then ſix Weeks takes from the Hollanders three whole Provinces of ſeven that compoſe their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, together with all the ſtrong For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39221:21"/>upon the Banks of the <hi>Vahal</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld <hi>Rhine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She ſeizes upon <hi>Franche Conte</hi> the ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime, and puſhes on her Conqueſts as far as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t was poſſible for her to do, with Orders to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her Forces to commit all the Ravages imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; allowing no Bounds to her vaſt Deſigns, then ſuch as the oppoſition of a greater Force was able to preſcribe her.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as ſhe had obtain'd her Ends, and ſaw her Affairs in a thriving condition, by the great Advantages which her victorious Arms had acquir'd, ſhe obſerv'd the ſame Conduct as ſhe obſerves at this day; that is to ſay, ſhe offer'd Propoſitions of Peace to the Confederates, rather to diſunite 'em, then out of any Compaſſion to the Calamities of <hi>Europe,</hi> as ſhe gave out, occaſion'd by the moſt bloody and cruel War that ever was known.</p>
            <p>Never was <hi>France</hi> more eager after Peace then at that time; there was never a petty Prince or State that was comprehended in the League, to whom ſhe did not make advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Offers; with a Deſign, that if ſhe could bring off any one, they who laſt laid down their Arms ſhould become Victims to her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, and their Territories, and their Countries be abandon'd to the Plunder and Fury of his Souldiers. I cannot here forbear to recite what the Marquiſs of <hi>Louvois</hi> ſaid one day to the King upon this occaſion. <q>Sir, ſaid he, if your Majeſty can but once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39221:22"/>the Princes of the League, <hi>France</hi> will have reaſon to admire her Happineſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and to boaſt of never having concluded ſo advantageous a Peace. To which purpoſe 'tis requiſite, that ſhe ſtoop to conſiderable Condeſcentions, and that ſhe offer to make Reſtitution of Places that may form a good Barrier in <hi>Flanders,</hi> for which ſhe may make her ſelf amends, by retaking 'em after the Concluſion of the Peace.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> V. having a deſign to enthral all <hi>Germany,</hi> finding himſelf ſo far from ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Enterpriſes, that he perceiv'd the liberty of the Princes, which he endeavour'd to oppreſs, gather Strength every day more then other, and that their Union became more Potent, reſolv'd to make 'em very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious Propoſals of Peace: as, likewiſe, to <hi>Francis</hi> I. the moſt formidable of all his Enemies, believing, that if he conſented once to an Accommodation, he ſhould eaſily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the reſt. And this is the Courſe that <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great takes at this day.</p>
            <p>However it were. <hi>France</hi> having luckily attain'd her end, after ſhe found the knack of ſeparating the <hi>Hollanders</hi> from their Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, ſurceaſes her offering Peace to the reſt, but impoſes the Law upon 'em, and forces 'em to an Acceptance, mangre their unwillingneſs. So that <hi>Spain</hi> was conſtrain'd to reſign Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocably and for ever <hi>Franche Conpte,</hi> together with the Cities of <hi>Valencionnes, Bouchain,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39221:22"/>Conde, Cambray, Aires, Sc. Omer, Ipres, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic</hi> and <hi>Warnton</hi> upon the <hi>Lis, Caſſel, Bovay, Maubege,</hi> with all their Signiores, Appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Dependences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> on the other ſide engages, but with <hi>Mazarin</hi>'s Mental Reſervation, to reſtore <hi>Charleroy, Binch, Ath, Oudenard</hi> and <hi>Countray,</hi> which had been reſign'd to her before the Treaty of <hi>Aix la Chapelle.</hi> In like manner, ſhe reſtor'd the Dutchy of <hi>Limberg,</hi> and the Country of <hi>Oultremouſe,</hi> together with the City and Citadel of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> the City of <hi>Leuve</hi> in <hi>Brabant,</hi> St. <hi>Ghilain</hi> in <hi>Hainault,</hi> and the City of <hi>Puicerda</hi> in <hi>Catalonia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now look how much <hi>France</hi> advances in the Negotiation of the Peace at <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> eſpecially after ſhe had found a way to ſatisfy the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whether to their content or no it matter'd not, but more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the foremoſt who were the principal Sinews of the League, ſhe raiſes her Tone a litter higher, and never concerns her ſelf with what the reſt of the Confederates will do: She knows what ſhe had to do, to bring 'em to her Bow. So that the Emperor, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Empire, and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who are the laſt to be agreed with, having nothing to do but to prepare for a new War, if they obſtinately ſtand out, and refuſe the Propoſitions that are made 'em, Blows imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately follow Threats; ſhe marches her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into the Territories of thoſe Princes, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39221:23"/>conſtrains 'em, by the unheard of Ravages and Cruelties there committed, to accept the ſevere Conditions which ſhe offers 'em, and ſo ſells 'em their Peace at a dear rate.</p>
            <p>After this manner the Treaty between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> was concluded in 1678. and the Emperor was fain to comply the next Year: Between whom and <hi>France</hi> it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, That his Imperial Majeſty and the moſt Chriſtian King, ſhould renew and confirm the Contents of the Treaty of <hi>Munſter</hi> in 1648. except in ſome Points.</p>
            <p>By this Treaty, the moſt Chriſtian King engages to reſign and transfer to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and his Heirs and Succeſſors, the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Right of Protection and Poſſeſſion of the City of <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> which he poſſeſs'd by vertue of the Peace of <hi>Munſter.</hi> On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, his Imperial Majeſty, in the name of the whole Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and of the Empire, promiſes to reſign and transfer to his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty and his Succeſſors, the City and Cittadel of <hi>Friburgh,</hi> with the three Villages depending upon it, excepting the Dioceſan Rights, which were reſerv'd to the Biſhop and Church of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> to which it belong'd.</p>
            <p>Next to the Emperor, the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh</hi> was forc'd, in his turn, to obey <hi>France,</hi> and to reſtore to <hi>Sweden</hi> all that he had won from that Crown; ſo that the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, finding himſelf the only innocent Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39221:23"/>of the Party, whoſe Intereſts he had ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enerouſly eſpous'd, laid it ſo heinouſly to Heart, as to vow, That if he had bin ſo eaſie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to the time paſt, to intermeddle with other Peoples Quarrels, he would be ſo prudent for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e future, as to conſider twice before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar'd once. What a Conſolation it was to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e moſt Chriſtian King, to ſee that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings went to wrack on the Confederates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de, after the Hollanders had quitted that Union. Therefore, moſt Serene Princes, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>othing ever be ſo prevalent as to diſunite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our Confederacy; for 'tis by your united <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orce that you will obtain a laſting and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urable Peace; nor is there any other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able Means to bring down the Pride of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>greed by the XII. Article, That he ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reſtor'd to the Territories which Duke <hi>Charles</hi> his Uncle enjoy'd in 1670. at what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime <hi>France</hi> made her ſelf Miſtreſs of 'em, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon condition that the City of <hi>Nanci</hi> and the Dependencies, ſhould belong to the King in Soveraignty. And it was alſo agreed, That beſides the Thorough-fare, which the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Duke had granted to his Majeſty in 1667. Prince <hi>Charles</hi> ſhould engage to allow him two more, from <hi>Nanci</hi> to <hi>Metz;</hi> and ſo unto <hi>Franche Conte.</hi> In this manner <hi>France</hi> conſents to the Reſtitution of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> as ſhe had done by the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace; but <hi>Colbert
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39221:24"/>Croiſſi,</hi> in imitation of <hi>Mazarin,</hi> labours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſerve a Thorough-fare and High Roa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for his Majeſties Forces, to the end that if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Fancy ſhould take him to ſeize upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Dukedom a third time, he may always find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> open and ready to receive him. Moreover the King engag'd by the XVII Article to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſign and transfer to him the Propriety an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Soveraignty of the City of <hi>Toul,</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Banlieu or Precinct of a League in compaſs belonging to it, to make him amends for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> loſs of <hi>Nanci. France</hi> had alſo promis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to give him in exchange for the City an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Provoſtſhip of <hi>Longwic,</hi> and Equivalent in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the three Biſhopricks: But ſhe made a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of that Article as well as of all the reſt. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the day of ſigning Treaties is once over, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> never thinks her ſelf bound to perform an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more.</p>
            <p>The Landgraviate of <hi>Alſatia,</hi> and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of that Province, the three Biſhop ricks of <hi>Metz, Toul</hi> and <hi>Verdun,</hi> and <hi>Sangovi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> with <hi>Briſac,</hi> were alſo to be reſign'd to <hi>France</hi> by the Treaties of <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Nime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After ſo many Reſignations and Surrenders one would have thought that this Ambitious Potentate ſhould have bin ſatisfied; but fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from that, he gave the Emperor to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, in a ſhort time after, that ſince he had ſurrender'd one part of that Province to him the whole belong'd to him by Rights of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39221:24"/>Convenience, Equivocation, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, and a thouſand other Chimerical Plaims, which he readily invented, and which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought Re-unions into Faſhion. So that the are Langraviate, with <hi>Briſac</hi> and <hi>Sandgaw,</hi> which lie in the upper <hi>Alſatia,</hi> being reſign'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, they muſt be taken for the whole <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatia,</hi> tho' they make but one part of it.</p>
            <p>As to the Government of the Province which only referr'd to the lower <hi>Alſatia,</hi> 'twas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>preſly agreed by the Treaty, That <hi>France</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould only enjoy the Right of the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ation of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> without appropriating to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſelf any Right of Soveraignty; but ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ugh'd at that Exception. So that 'twas a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anifeſt Uſurpation, and a meer pretence to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppreſs the Liberty of all <hi>Alſatia,</hi> as being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>veſted with a ſingle Prerogative: That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iberty, which had been always ſo dear to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat Province, and which it had enjoy'd for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o many Years, as a Member of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire.</p>
            <p>I would fain know to what purpoſe ſerv'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the Care and Pains which the Emperors Plenipotentiaries took, to inſert expreſly the Names of the Countries and Places which were to be reſign'd to the Emperor, and which were not to be ſurrender'd. 'Twas ſaid, That the Landgraviat, and all the reſt of <hi>Alſatia,</hi> ſhould enjoy the ſame Franchiſes and Privileges which they had enjoy'd under the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> But <hi>France</hi> paſſing by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39221:25"/>all theſe Reſervations made a Jeſt of 'em, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> uſing the Lands that were not ſurrender'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſame Pride and Cruelty, as thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were, has ſo order'd the Matter, that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of that Province have ſufficiently exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd the rigorous Effecrs of his Tyranny.</p>
            <p>It would require a large Volume to enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate all the Articles that <hi>France</hi> has viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and, therefore, we ſhall refer thoſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> deſire a more particular Account, to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Authors who have diſcours'd at large up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Negotiation of the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All <hi>Europe</hi> wearied with ſo many Breach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and wicked Incroachments, panted after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thing but Peace, and prepar'd to enjoy it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome Years; and there was ſome reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hope, that <hi>France</hi> having reap'd ſuch a plen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Harveſt of Advantages from the Alli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> would have ſet bounds to her Deſigns, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> liv'd in perfect Unionw ith the Houſe of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> and the reſt of the Princes of <hi>Europ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> But neither is all this any thing: Her Limi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are not yet enough extended; nor will an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thing leſs content heer, then the Limits of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whole Earth.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon why I cannot here forbear t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> recite the words of St. <hi>Auſtin, To make Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> upon our Neighbours, and thence to carry it ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> farther into other Countries, oppreſſing People that never did us harm, and this meerly out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> an Ambitious Deſire of Empire; what is it elſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but a glorious ſort of Robbing upon the High<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:39221:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>way?</hi> Thus, in a few Words, you have the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of all the Heroick Vertues of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eat, his Panegyrick in Miniature. To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ich we may add, thoſe Verſes of <hi>Juvenal,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eaking of the Inſatiable deſire of <hi>Alexander,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aggrandize his Fame.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Pellaeo Juveni non ſufficit Orbis:</l>
               <l>Aeſtuat Infoelix Anguſto Limite mundi,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Gyarae clauſus ſcopulis, Parvo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſeripho.</l>
               <l>Cum tamen a figulis munitam intraverit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem,</l>
               <l>Sarcophago contentus erit—</l>
            </q>
            <p>That Prince who was too little for the Univerſe, and the Univerſe too little for him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d whoſe Ambition could never be aſſwag'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing enter'd into <hi>Babylon,</hi> was forc'd to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntented with a ſingle Coffin.</p>
            <p>My Opinion is, that as much may be ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, and that this ſwelling Monarch, having bin the Scourge of his Age, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Terror of his Enemies, and the moſt Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Prince that ever ſway'd the Scepter of <hi>France,</hi> will be at length conſtrain'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine the vaſt extent of his Deſigns, and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable deſire of Aggrandizing himſelf, to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>canty Tomb prepar'd for him at St. <hi>Denis</hi>'s, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here to be laid up among the Illuſtrious and High-born Lumber of the World. But this is not the Buſineſs in hand; we muſt ſtay till he's dead. In the mean time, let us ſee
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39221:26"/>what he has done further. He has violat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, and that of <hi>Aix la Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelle;</hi> now let us conſider, whether he held <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Peace of <hi>Nimeguen</hi> more ſacred or more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> violable.</p>
            <p>In the Year, 1688. <hi>France</hi> makes her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Miſtreſs of two the moſt Important Places <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Europe:</hi> To which purpoſe, obſerve the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices that <hi>Luovis</hi> makes uſe of. He co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceals his Order of Knighthood under his u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Coat, puts himſelf into a Diſguize, tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Poſt-Horſes, and flies from <hi>Verſailles,</hi> attent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only by one ſingle Lacquey, and comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>cognito</hi> to <hi>Strasburgh.</hi> Being arriv'd at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Entrance into the Plain, within Canon-ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the City, there he found the Coach of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chief Burgo-maſter of the Town, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for his coming; into which he whipp'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fear of being known, and order'd his Lacque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> who was alſo in the Diſguiſe of a Hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> courſer, to go before with the two Horſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and lodge at the <hi>White Horſe,</hi> where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſtay, and make a ſhew of trucking for Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, till he had notice of the Day and He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of his return.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Louvois</hi> was conducted to the Chief Burge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> maſter's Houſe, who had found a way to rid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> himſelf of his Wife and Children, by ſending 'em to his Houſe in the Country, about thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Leagues from the City, keeping no Body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> attend him at home, but a very faithful <hi>Val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> de Chambre.</hi> The reſt of the Magiſtrates that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:39221:26"/>were of the Cabal, were to randezouze in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Night-time; and as ſoon as they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> together, they fell to the Buſineſs. <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vois</hi> began the Treaty with a Propoſal of great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dvantages and Rewards which his Majeſty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſerv'd particularly for them, after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſion of an Affair, which he lookt upon as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Concern of great Importance to his other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſigns. And to render his Chapmen the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ore favourable, he added to his other Marks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Friendſhip and Acknowledgment, ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urſes of 500 <hi>Luidores</hi> apiece, of which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſented one to every particular Perſon, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng 'em with a Smile, at the time that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade the Preſents, <hi>That his Majeſty was not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rich as fully to remunerate the great Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons which they were about to confer upon him; however, that they had to do with a Prince, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>anted neither Good-will nor Power to make 'em Great Lords in</hi> France.</p>
            <p>At the Fourth Conference 'twas agreed, That <hi>Louvois</hi> ſhould engage for the payment of 400000. Livers in ready Mony to the Chief Burgo-maſter, and that every one of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſts, Conſuls and Magiſtrates the were of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Cabal, ſhould have for their ſhare 300000 Livers; in conſideration of which, the Keys of the City ſhould be put into his Hands; and the ſaid City was to be put into his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Hands, to reck'n from the <hi>23d</hi> of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1661. which was the Day made choice of for his Majeſties taking Livery and Seizſin.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39221:27"/>Beſides that, <hi>Louvois</hi> engag'd to allo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſaid Magiſtrates their Houſe-Rent fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> at his Majeſties Charge, from the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Arrival at <hi>Paris,</hi> aſſuring 'em of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Majeſties Friendſhip and Protection, again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all that ſhould make any Attempt upon the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> having thus made her ſelf Miſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Capital City of <hi>Alſatia, Louvois</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> word to the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> that if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a mind to quit <hi>Caſal</hi> for Mony, he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him down two Millions upon the Nail. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Importance of that Negotiation, and the fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Court was in leſt the Secret ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vulg'd, caus'd his Majeſty to make choice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Colbert Croiſſi,</hi> in the abſence of <hi>Louvois,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had proffer'd to undertake a Journey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Italy,</hi> as he had done into <hi>Alſatia,</hi> but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Fatigues of his firſt Journey would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> permit him. At length <hi>Colbert Croiſſi</hi> depa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all haſte, after he had receiv'd full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtructions, and came to <hi>Caſal Incognit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> where he had a Conference Face to Face <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Duke. As they were about to take the leaves, after the firſt Treaty which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> together, <hi>Colbert</hi> pulling out ſome Papers out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Pocket, unluckily let fall his Memoirs u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Table, which the Duke took up, ſo ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as the Miniſter was gone out of the Room<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and having read 'em, he found the Purport <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 'em to be, That in caſe the Duke made a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſcruple to part with <hi>Caſal</hi> for two Millio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:39221:27"/>
               <hi>Colbert</hi> ſhould come up to his Price what-ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were, and that if he only ſtook for Mony, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at he ſhould mount up to four Millions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aving the reſt to his Prudence. But above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things, he had order not to return, till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Affair was fully concluded.</p>
            <p>The next day in the Morning, coming to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tend the Duke, as he was dreſſing himſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Prince's Pages neatly ſlipt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emoire into the Miniſters Pocket, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing perceiv'd; and then the Duke making <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if he knew nothing of his Orders, told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, 'Twas impoſſible to deliver up ſuch an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>portant Place as <hi>Caſal,</hi> under leſs then four <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>illions in Silver, and that he expected 'em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be paid upon the Day that the Town was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be deliver'd, or immediately after ſigning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Treaty. <hi>Colbert</hi> was extreamly ſurpriz'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hear that the Duke's Mind was ſo ſtrangely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er'd from what it was the Day before, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gning that he would return home without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing any thing, told the Duke, that he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as much as lay in his Power, and that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould preſume to exceed his Maſter's Orders <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> far as ſome few hundred thouſand Livres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould reach, above the two Millions that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> offer'd the Day before. 'Twas agreed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, That his Maſter ſhould give 500000 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>vres more, above the Two Millions that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> offer'd the Day before, together with an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nnual Penſion of 200000, which ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gularly paid during his Life. Upon this,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39221:28"/>the poor Prince fell into the Snare, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> glitter of the <hi>French Lewidores</hi> daz'ld him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that degree, that he ſign'd the Contract of Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Colbert</hi> returned to Court in leſs then Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Weeks.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>France</hi> became the Miſtreſs of Tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtrong Barriers, without ſo much as drawin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Sword, which ſecur'd her both on <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> ſide. Beſides theſe notorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts upon the Peace, the moſt Chriſtian King beſieg'd <hi>Courtray,</hi> and won it. Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> done, he ſpent no leſs then 3000 Bombs up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> and laid it in Aſhes. If the <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> complain of theſe Cruelties, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſwers 'em, That the Marquis of <hi>Grana</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> committed Acts of Hoſtility, which he nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſo much as dreamt of, and then, like a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Man, lets looſe all his Fury, and ſends <hi>Bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers</hi> and <hi>Montal</hi> to commit all the Ravag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> imaginable; orders 'em to waſte all befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 'em with Fire and Sword, to the very Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Mons,</hi> and to act thoſe Villanies and Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties in the midſt of Peace, that ſcarce cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have bin committed in the height of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bloody War.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Charles</hi> the Bold, Duke of <hi>Burgun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had the Sir-name of <hi>Terrible</hi> given him 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Years after his Death, becauſe he renew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Rigour of War in former Times, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which had been diſcontinued for ſome Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> among the Chriſtians; it may be ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great has out-done him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:39221:28"/>never any Prince has rendred himſelf more Terrible in Hiſtory, or more odious to the World, then this Monarch has made himſelf, by his Cruelties and Barbarities, during the whole Courſe of his Reign. But let us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the other Breaches of the Peace.</p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian King, perceiving that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> lay ſecure and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs, and that not ſo much as one of 'em ſtirr'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o oppoſe his Deſigns, while every one minded noting but his own particular Intereſts, thought himſelf at Liberty to do whatever he pleas'd. Thereupon, he bethought himſelf of building Fortreſſes along the <hi>Rhine,</hi> upon the Territories of his Enemies, and Barriers and Securities of his Conqueſts, but which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd their Dominions to the firſt Fury and Havocks of a War, in caſe of a Rupture, and enabl'd him to carry his Arms into the Heart of <hi>Germany,</hi> before the Forces of the Empire could be in a Condition to march. With this Deſign he erected that important Fortreſs of <hi>Mount-Royal</hi> upon the <hi>Moſelle,</hi> within the Peninſula of <hi>Trebon,</hi> upon a ſteep Rock, almoſt encompaſs'd with the River: he fortiy'd <hi>Sar-Lewis</hi> upon the <hi>Sar;</hi> and rais'd the Fort of <hi>Huninghen,</hi> conſiſting of Five Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, ſeated upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> with a wooden Bridge a little below <hi>Bale</hi> in <hi>Sungouw.</hi> To which we may add the Forts which he rais'd upon the <hi>Rhine</hi> near <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:39221:29"/>
            <p>When theſe Enormous Actions were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of in <hi>France,</hi> the Anſwer was ready <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> For the Imperial Miniſters were told, That their Maſter had no reaſon to be jealous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what ſhe did; for that ſhe was very well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd, there was nothing done contrary to the Peace.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1684. <hi>France</hi> gives the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King to underſtand, that he was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver into her Hands the Equivalent that had bin offer'd her, in lieu of the Country o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Aloſt,</hi> and upon the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s refuſing immediately to ſatisfy her new Pretenſions, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. lays Siege to <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> and in leſs then a Month makes him Maſter of that important Fortreſs, the Key of all <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After ſhe had thus worry'd all <hi>Europe,</hi> ſhe bethought her ſelf of citeing the Princes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Empire before Soveraign Courts and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunals, erected at <hi>Mets</hi> and <hi>Briſac,</hi> where French Commiſſioners, being both Judges and Parties, pronounc'd Sentences of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, by vertue of certain Parchments gnaw'd by the Rats and ſoyl'd with Duſt and Smoak, to the end they might look old, and conſequently the more Authentick. Which Writings being drawn by a Famous Advocate of <hi>Paris,</hi> contain'd Claims and Pretenſions of <hi>France,</hi> to ſeveral States, Signiories and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by vertue of Reunions and Dependencies of Lands, which had been granted by the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39221:29"/>Treaties of <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen.</hi> But 'tis to be obſerv'd, that theſe Claims were ſo much the more Imaginary and Chimerical, becauſe it had been agreed by the Articles of the Treaties, That <hi>France</hi> ſhould renounce 'em: Yet all thoſe Renunciations were not able to put a ſtop to her. She had always one Code or Digeſt, at hand, apart by themſelves; and when ſhe had a fancy to deſpoil any Prince of his Territories, or to ſeize upon any Lands that lay convenient for her, ſhe never fail'd of a Pretence. Her Laws were like a Saddle, for all Horſes, and ſhe gave 'em what Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation ſhe pleas'd: So that 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee her Commenting upon all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Treaties, and wreſting the Senſe to her own Advantage.</p>
            <p>Two Months after the taking of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, France</hi> perceiving that that New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt had manifeſtly diſcover'd her Ambition, and ſet the Low Countries and all <hi>Germany</hi> a Murmuring, and very near incens'd 'em to a new War, and diſappoint her Deſigns, which were, ſtill to be gaining at a cheap rate, under the ſhadow of Peace, bethought her ſelf of one of the neateſt knacks of Policy that ever ſhe was guilty of. She propos'd to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, to <hi>Spain,</hi> and the States General of the United Provinces, a Truce of twenty Years; and in regard her Armies were ſtill marching at the ſame time that ſhe makes her Demands, that ſhe may be able to make 'em good, ſhe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39221:30"/>order'd her Embaſſadors to let thoſe Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates underſtand, That if they refus'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the advantagious Offers of a Truce to ſecure the Repoſe and Tranquility of Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endom, ſhe was reſolv'd to declare open War againſt 'em. Who would have thought, but that <hi>France</hi> had then bin full of Sincerity and good Will? To hear the Language of her Embaſſadors and Plenipotentiaries, a Man would have ſworn, That the Truce would infallibly have prov'd more ſacred and invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable then the three preceding Treaties.</p>
            <p>The Hollanders were the firſt that fell into the Snare, in hopes to have enjoy'd a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and durable Peace; a Lure which <hi>France</hi> has all along dextrouſly made uſe of when ever ſhe had a deſign to amuſe the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who ſeeing himſelf the continual mark of that Ambitious Crown, was willing to have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd his poor Countries from the Ravages to which they were expos'd, and to deliver 'em from the Miſchiefs they had ſuffer'd for almoſt thirty Years together: And, therefore, for theſe Reaſons they conſented to a Truce for 20 Years. The Emperor, who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready engag'd in a War with the Ottoman Port, whoſe prodigious Numbers made all <hi>Germany</hi> tremble, found himſelf in a kind of Neceſſity to temporize with <hi>France,</hi> for fear of drawing that powerful and dangerous Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my upon his Shoulders, and ſo ſubmitted to the Truce after the Example of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:39221:30"/>
            <p>And thus you ſee how the moſt Chriſtian King obtain'd his Ends. For by this Treaty he ſecur'd his Conqueſts, lull'd the Holland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers aſleep, and amus'd the Emperor and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Empire: All theſe Potentates being ſo credulous as to fall into the Snare, maugre the Experience they had ſo many times al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready had of his Infidelity. What does <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great do after this? He prepares to bring to an abſolute Concluſion, the Grand Work which his Ambition had ſet on foot; and which he had bin labouring to bring about for above forty Years together, I mean, the Univerſal Monarchy. To which purpoſe, there was no Precaution which that Prince did not take. He ally'd himſelf to the Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Port; he diſpatch'd away Marſhal <hi>d' Humiers</hi> to the Court of <hi>England,</hi> and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges King <hi>James</hi> to ſide with him: He pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes the Friendſhip of <hi>Poland</hi> and the Czars of <hi>Muſcovy;</hi> he propoſes Offers to the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern Crowns and the Princes of <hi>Italy;</hi> he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to gain the three Eccleſiaſtical Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and to appoint Coadjutors that were devoted to his Intereſts: He does all he can to carry <hi>Fuſtenburgh</hi>'s Election; he quarrels with the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> he revokes the Edict of <hi>Nants,</hi> drives the Reformed out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; makes ſtrict Alliances with the King of <hi>Siam</hi> to ruin the Hollanders's Trade; and bargains with the <hi>Switzers</hi> what he ſhall give 'em to ſit ſtill and look on.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:39221:31"/>
            <p>We might here give a particular Accoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the great Preparations of <hi>France</hi> to ſprin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Mines that were to make her Miſtreſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the ſtrong Holds of <hi>Europe.</hi> She reckon'd upon the Conqueſt of the Remainder of the Low Countries and <hi>Holland,</hi> as a certain and infallible thing. King <hi>James</hi> had given him a Promiſe of it, and that Prince's word was Irrevocable. <hi>Germany</hi> being at the ſame time attack'd by all the Forces of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Turky,</hi> muſt have ſunk under the Burthen, and have become the Prey of potent Enemies: And at the ſame time likewiſe all the Dominions of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> were juſt ready to change their Maſter, and to ſee themſelves ſubdu'd under the French Monarchy, which was to have no other Limits then thoſe of all <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian King had ſo ſurely built upon theſe Foundations, and had taken ſuch true Meaſures, that a Man might have juſtly ſaid, That nothing could have ſtopp'd him. But then of a ſudden happens the Blow which could only do the Buſineſs, a Blow the moſt fatal and deadly that ever happen'd to <hi>France,</hi> and which render'd abortive all her Deſigns in an inſtant; ranverſes that <hi>Coloſſus</hi> of Pride and Ambition that had bin Erected upon the Ruins of ſo many poor States and Sover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aignties, at the expence of Treaties broken, and which conſiſted only in the hopes of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading the reſt that lay fit for Convenience. I mean, the Revolution of <hi>England;</hi> the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39221:31"/>Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> his vow'd Enemy, is made King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and made it appear, That only <hi>England</hi> was able to deliver <hi>Europe</hi> from the oppreſſion of the French Crown.</p>
            <p>And, now moſt Serene Princes, you are within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> very little of reducing <hi>France</hi> within the Bounds of the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace, if your Union ſubſiſts but two Campaigns longer. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whatever Advantages <hi>France</hi> propoſes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow ſoft and obliging ſo ever her Careſſes may be, reject 'em all. Let the Experience of what is paſt, inſtruct ye to avoid at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent what has been the Ruin of all the Leagues that have been formerly contracted againſt her. You have to do with a crafty and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Enemy; and as ſhe has found the Benefit of her Maxims practis'd in the late Wars, ſhe makes uſe, at preſent, of the ſame to break your Union.</p>
            <p>How earneſt is ſhe at the Court of <hi>Rome?</hi> How importunate with the Northern Crowns and the laudable Cantons to perſuade 'em to take the Meditation upon 'em? To this purpoſe ſhe ſpares neither Gold nor Silver, nor Embaſſies, and it is in good part diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, that ſhe offer'd ſix Millions to any one that could procure a Peace. And which is worſe, we find to our Sorrow, that her Pains have not prov'd altogether fruitleſs, by the Steps that ſome People tread, who intereſt themſelves too much in her Concerns.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:39221:32"/>
            <p>But ſome zealous Adherents to that Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will object and ſay, That 'tis high time to pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſtop to the Miſeries that afflict <hi>Europe,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you ought not any longer to refuſe that Peac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>France</hi> which ſhe demands, ſince ſhe make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch advantagious Offers, ſeeing the Denia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will render you reſponſible before God fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the Blood that is ſhed and for all the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Calamities that attend War. The mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtian King, ſay they, offers the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates Conditions altogether reaſonable; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offers 'em Barriers ſufficient to ſecure thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Liberty, and to ſecure 'em for the future from the prodigious Forces of that Crown. Thoſe Offers are theſe that follow:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> propoſes, by the Daniſh Envoy, That firſt in reſpect of the Emperor, the Princes and States of the Empire, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> the Advantages which his Armies have gain'd upon his Enemies, ſhall make no alteration in the Conditions that have bin communicated to his Daniſh Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
            <p>That in reſpect of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty might juſtly keep all his Conqueſts after the Example of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Kings; but that to facilitate a Peace, he is willing to reſtore <hi>Roſes</hi> and <hi>Belevers,</hi> and, in a word, all that he has conquer'd in <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia,</hi> during this laſt War. He adds, That he had ſtill more reaſon to keep, for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Frontiers, all the Conqueſts that he
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39221:32"/>had won in <hi>Flanders,</hi> yet for the forming of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Barrier that might remove all occaſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſquiet from the United Provinces, he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtore to the King of <hi>Spain, Mons</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ur,</hi> and offer'd to demoniſh <hi>Charleroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Country of <hi>Liege,</hi> he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore the City and Caſtle of <hi>Huy</hi> to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoprick, and make amends for <hi>Dinant</hi> and <hi>Bouilion,</hi> by reuniting ſuch a Portion of the Country of <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> as ſhould lie moſt for the convenience of the Biſhoprick, and as ſhould be deem'd reaſonable by choſen Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trators.</p>
            <p>He conſents to the re-ſettling of Trade with the States General, according to the Agreements in the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Alteration.</p>
            <p>In caſe of the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Death, he conſents that the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy thoſe Countries, provided the Emperor will declare the ſame to be his Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: And, that tho' the Deceaſed Queen's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation to <hi>Spain</hi> during her Minority be Void, for the Reaſons already made publick to the World, his Majeſty is willing, as well for himſelf as for the Dauphin, to confirm he ſaid Renunciation in favour of the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> with all the requiſite Formalities; adding withall, that he makes no queſtion but that this Engagement will convince the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates beyond all other things of the reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Peace which he propoſes to 'em.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:39221:33"/>
            <p>As to the Affairs of <hi>England,</hi> the Royal Majeſty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being wounded in the Perſon of the K. of Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Britain,</hi> his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty makes no queſtion but that the King of <hi>Sweeden</hi> and the Emperor himſelf will propoſe ſome Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to put an end to that Difference: And moreover his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty has no pretention directly nor indirectly to <hi>England;</hi> excepting what he claim'd during this War to the Iſlands and Continents of <hi>America,</hi> of which he demands Reſtitution, being ready to renew with that Crown the laſt Treaty of Commerce, which was in force when the War began.</p>
            <p>As for what concerns <hi>Germany,</hi> his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty-conſents, that the Treaty of <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> ſhall remain in full Force and Vigour.</p>
            <p>That the Truce in 1684. might be chang'd into a Definitive Treaty of Peace; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs with theſe Exceptions.</p>
            <p>That in compenſation for <hi>Strasburg, France</hi> ſhall Surrender up <hi>Mont Royal</hi> and <hi>Trarbag,</hi> after the Fortifications are Demoliſh'd, grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it be for the ſecurity of the Empire. Beſides that, his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty will reſtore <hi>Philipsbourg</hi> and <hi>Fribourg</hi> to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and the Empire, together with the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications, in the ſame condition as now they are. That Fort <hi>Lewis</hi> and <hi>Huninghen</hi> ſhall be Demoliſh'd: That <hi>Heydelburg</hi> and the <hi>Palatinat</hi> ſhall be reſtor'd to the Palatinate; <hi>France</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39221:33"/>upon her to make Madam amends for the Succeſſion of the Electors her Father and Brother; an Article which his Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Majeſty ſtands very much upon.</p>
            <p>In regard of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Moſt Chriſtian King conſents that the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen</hi> ſhall be obſerv'd, <hi>Sar Louis, Briche</hi> and <hi>Hombourg</hi> excepted, for which there ſhall be an Equivalent given of an equal Revenue.</p>
            <p>That the moſt Serene Republic of <hi>Venice</hi> ſhall be Arbitratrix if there be any Reunions to make; and for the putting a concluſion to all Differences between <hi>France</hi> and the reſt of the Princes, ſhe will agree to any juſt and reaſonable Propoſals that ſhall be made on their Part and in their Name.</p>
            <p>In truth, we muſt acknowledge, that <hi>France</hi> is become all on a ſudden very Tractable and very Conſciencious; ſhe who was wont to gripe all, and reſtore nothing, now offers the Confederates the Reſtitution of all the Places during the laſt War.</p>
            <p>Moſt Serene Princes, here is a particular Favour, which the Moſt Chriſtian King vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes ye: He is willing notwithſtanding your Obſtinacy to continue the War, to heap his Graces upon ye, to the end you may have reaſon to forget the Miſchiefs he has done ye. He offers to be Reconcil'd with ye, and lay down his Arms, provided you will accept of his Propoſitions of Peace, and rely upon his Promiſes.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:39221:34"/>
            <p>After this, 'tis to be thought, that you will have no cauſe to Complain: And the Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of <hi>France</hi> will be apt to tell ye, that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. is at this day Triumphant and Victorious, and conſequently that 'tis for him to give Laws to his Enemies, and to make no Reſtitutions at all, but what he pleaſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But to this I anſwer, If <hi>France</hi> has got ſuch great Advantages over the Princes of the League, and is ſo much a gainer by the War, why do's ſhe talk of Peace? To ſpare you therefore the pains of alledging ſome good Reaſon or other, in juſtification of a Prince whoſe Intereſts you ſo heartily Maintain; I ſhall only repeat what <hi>Mazarine</hi> upon the like occaſion wrote to M. <hi>Lionne,</hi> Secretary of State, concerning the Negotiation of the <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaean</hi> Peace. <hi>For as to what remains,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I ſhould make no ſcruple to acknowledge the ſeeking after Peace, when the Progreſs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the King's Arms in the next Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pain, ſhall have advanced his Majesties Renown to the higheſt pitch it can arrive at,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the Sentiments of the moſt Subtle and Crafty Miniſter that ever <hi>France</hi> had, who decides the Queſtion in few words. The Moſt Chriſtian King has ſo well profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Maxims of that great Politician, that 'tis with him an inviolable Law not to ſwerve from the Practice thereof to this day. Nor was <hi>Mazarin</hi> alone of this Opinion: The Marqueſs of <hi>Louvois</hi> jumps with him in the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:39221:34"/>ſame Sentiments. And tho' he were not of ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ublime a Genius as <hi>Mazarin,</hi> the Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he acquir'd during his Miniſtry, renders <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im Authentic enough to be quoted for a good Author. You ſhall hear what he ſaid to <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Croiſſi,</hi> when he gave him his laſt Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions how to carry himſelf at the Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> whither he was ſent with the Character of a Plenipotentiary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know very well,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Princes will make a Judgment to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of his Majeſty, of his Conduct in inviting 'em to a Peace; but it matters not, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages he will receive thereby, will amply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence the Wrong which his Honour will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; beſides that, we ſhall come off well enough by giving out that his Majeſty vouchſaf'd to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Peace to</hi> Europe.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what has been all along the Temper of <hi>France;</hi> this is no Maxim of Ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, as being practis'd by ſeveral of his Majeſty's Anceſtors: Witneſs what <hi>Comines</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of <hi>Lewis</hi> XI. That that ſame Prince to get himſelf out of the Bryars at a time when <hi>Paris,</hi> the Capital City of his Kingdom was within a very little of being Beſieg'd by the <hi>Burgundians,</hi> deem'd it the only way in the World he could take, to Temporize. He thought it by no means proper to venture his Kingdom upon the Hazard of a Battle, and therefore labour'd under-hand to Diſ-unite the Princes and Lords of the Confederacy;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39221:35"/>which ſucceeded very luckily, and by that means he got the better of his Enemies. <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. took the ſame Courſe: And ſtill when <hi>France</hi> has been overwhelm'd with the great number of her Enemies, it has been always her way to ruin their Union with fair and plauſible Propoſals of Peace.</p>
            <p>But if it may be ſaid, that the French Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy had always Great Maſters in this Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enice, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV has out-done 'em all: His Reign has been a continued Series of deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Promiſes, violated Faith, and Treaties bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. In a word, this Prince obſerving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Attack'd by the moſt Potent Confederacy that ever was entred into againſt <hi>France,</hi> can never take a better opportunity to propoſe Peace then when her Triumphant Arms may ſeem to boaſt of ſome Advantages. The ſame Arms are fickle and uncertain, and Fortune that has favour'd him hitherto, may forſake him, and reduce his Affairs to the moſt Piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Condition in the World. It looks then, if we may judge of Events by the diſpoſal and management of things, as if <hi>France</hi> affraid of ſtrange Revolutions, ſufficient to raviſh from him in an inſtant, all the Honour and Glories he has hitherto enjoy'd, and deſpoil her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts gain'd by breach of Treaties, ſought to effect by Policy what ſhe cannot compaſs by Force.</p>
            <p>There are four things that urge the Crown of <hi>France</hi> to preſs the Confederates ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39221:35"/>for a Treaty of Peace. The Firſt, is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ondition of her Affairs, which at preſent is ſavourable enough, in regard of the Progreſſes which her Arms have made. The Second is, her Apprehenſions, leſt the Confederates con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably augmenting their Forces and redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling their Efforts, ſhould weaken her in ſuch a manner, as to diſable her for the future from making a further Progreſs upon her Neighbours, if they permit her to keep her own. The Third is, the hopes that ſhe has of luckily obtaining her ends by the ſame Artifices which ſhe made uſe of at the Peace of <hi>Nimiguen.</hi> And the Fourth is, the low ebb of her Exchequer, and the deplorable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People, reduc'd to utmoſt Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by Famin and want of Corn.</p>
            <p>As to the condition of her Affairs, moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that <hi>France</hi> is well advis'd in tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this time to make her Propoſals of Peace. She was never ſo happy, nor ſo much careſs'd by Fortune as now. For five Years together, that the War has bin declar'd, excepting the Firſt Campaign, wherein the Confederates triumph'd, upon the reducing of <hi>Mayence, Keiſerwart, Bon,</hi> &amp;c. to which we may add, that famous Atchievment at the <hi>Boyn,</hi> the memorable Victory with which it was attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Engagement by Sea, and the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Irruption into the Dauphinate; all other things may be ſaid to have been proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous for <hi>France.</hi> So that if ſhe could invea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39221:36"/>the Confederate Princes into a Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at a time when every thing ſmiles upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her, ſhe may have juſt reaſon to expect tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a Negotiation will be attended with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Peace, no leſs glorious and advantagious fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her, then that of the <hi>Pyreneans, Aix la Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelle</hi> or <hi>Nimeguen.</hi> For proof of which, then needs no more but to reflect upon the Offer of the Envoys of <hi>Denmark</hi> to the Court o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England</hi> and the States of the United Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which we have already recited. Which Offers are ſo inconſiderable, That 'tis a mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Inſulting, and an Affront put upon the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of ſo many Princes, to preſume that they would ever liſten to ſuch Propoſals.</p>
            <p>As to the Apprehenſions of. <hi>France</hi> leſt the Confederates ſhould redouble their Efforts, and conſtrain the moſt Chriſtian King to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine himſelf within much narrower Limits, 'tis as certain, That her Fears are not ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; and that 'tis but good Counſel given to the moſt Chriſtian King to adviſe him to bid his Generals and his Souldiers whet their Swords betimes, and have their Arms in a readineſs, becauſe that in all Likelihood we ſhall have a warm Campaign of it.</p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian King, perhaps, did ne're expect that <hi>England,</hi> turmoil'd as ſhe had been with Factions and Diſſentions, that harraſs'd the Peace and Tranquility of the Kingdom, would have taken a Reſolution to conclude the War by Efforts of Puiſſance and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39221:36"/>conſtant Oppoſition, by granting the Men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Mony which King <hi>William</hi> deſir'd. Nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England</hi> the only Confederate ſo well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in'd to the common Cauſe: The United <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rovinces, and the reſt of the Princes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tates that compoſe the League, unanimouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onclude, to ſacrifice the whole toward the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>btaining a laſting and durable Peace. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence it is that we behold ſuch numerous Armies, ſuch prodigious Forces muſter'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether on the Confederates ſide, amounting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s they ſay, to no leſs then 400000 Men: Which, if it be true, <hi>France</hi> will find it a difficult Task to fend off the Blows on every ſide. And I am perſuaded, that Marſhal <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> as much pufft up as he is with the Advantages that he obtain'd by number, will be conſtrain'd to acknowledge himſelf miſtaken, when he promis'd the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that he would ſing <hi>Te deum,</hi> before the end of <hi>April,</hi> in the Cathedral of <hi>Maeſtrich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to his hopes of attaining his Ends by means of the ſame Artifices which he made uſe of at the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> that you may be plainly convinc'd of it, there needs no more then to reflect upon the Conduct which he obſerves in reſpect of every Prince in particular, and of all in general, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite and draw 'em off the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He began with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> upon whom he put the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> believing his Highneſs might be wrought to a Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39221:37"/>when touched in the moſt ſenſible part, which was, when he came to be impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun'd by the Dutcheſs, his Wife.</p>
            <p>It may be ſaid, that ſhe omitted nothing to infuſe into him favourable Sentiments in the behalf of <hi>France.</hi> She has been ſeen to weep warm Tears, to fall upon her Knees and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Prince her Husband, beſeeching him with all the Tenderneſs imaginable, To put an end to the War; to have Compaſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Family and his haraſs'd Territories, and laſtly to rememember that <hi>France</hi> was only able to reſtore him to his ancient Liberty. She alſo deliver'd to him Letters, written with the King's own Hand, wherein that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch promis'd him, upon the Faith of a Prince, that he would forget what was paſt, and that he was ready to grant him all the Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that he could deſire. That to render the Peace the more venerable and inviolable, it ſhould be ſeal'd for a perpetual Alliance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Houſes, to which his Majeſty would add the Marriage of one of the Sons of <hi>France</hi> with the young Dutcheſs of <hi>Savoy,</hi> when they ſhould be of Age, which would knit thoſe indiſſoluble Knots, that nothing would be able to unty for the future, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After he had thus aſſail'd the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> what Springs did he not ſet at work in the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> to gain their Favour, and incline the Pope openly to favour his Intereſts, by inculcating into the Catholic Princes the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39221:37"/>Neceſſity of Breaking thoſe Engagements <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat united 'em with the Proteſtants. A Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, added he, that drew after it the inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able Deſtruction of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rected. Hereſie upon the Ruins of it, if the Holy Father did not ſave it, by inſpiring into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Emperor, the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the reſt of the Cotholick Princes ſpeedy Inclinations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o reconcile themſelves with <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his Imperial Majeſty, what Pains <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as he Court of <hi>France</hi> not taken to draw him off from the reſt of the Confederates? And finding that all the Importunities of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> wrought no impreſſion upon the Mind of that Prince, and that nothing was able to ſhake his Conſtancy, did not the moſt Chriſtian King diſpatch an Expreſs to the Court of <hi>Vienna,</hi> to preſent the Emperor with a Treaty of ſeparate Peace, and make him very advantagious Offers, if he would but conſent to it? After he had gone thus forward, did he not publiſh a <hi>Manifeſto</hi> upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and in all the Courts of <hi>Germany,</hi> to engage the Princes and States of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to lay down their Arms, and ſtand Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or elſe to accept the Propoſals already made 'em?</p>
            <p>What has he left undone to obtain the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of the Northern Crowns, of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick of <hi>Venice,</hi> of the laudable Cantons, to incline thoſe Potentates to eſpouſe his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts? Has he not ſent away Embaſſie upon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39221:38"/>Embaſſie, and how many Millions has he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd beſides? The Count <hi>d'Avaux</hi> offer'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sweden</hi> the Reſtitution of the Dutchy of <hi>Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ponts,</hi> and repayment of all the Loſſes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain'd, reckoning from the very firſt Day tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>France</hi> made herſelf Miſtreſs of it; beſide four Millions, and 500000 Livres, which would be actually paid down, together with a Penſion of 200000 Livres, if his <hi>Swediſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Majeſty would effectually interpoſe his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation with King <hi>William,</hi> the moſt zealou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for continuance of the War. Upon the Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s refuſal to accept theſe Offers <hi>Bonrepos</hi> offer'd the Court of <hi>Denmark</hi> Six millions, together with Mademoiſelle <hi>de</hi>— to be given in Marriage to the Prince Roya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> according to the Project begu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at <hi>Paris,</hi> before the departure of that Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty offering, beſides, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pay the Dowry, and to decree all things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the Ratification of the Peace And the Steps which the Envoys of his Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Majeſty tread both in the Court of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and in <hi>Holland,</hi> have made it appear that thoſe Offers were not made in vain. Now let us ſee what Propoſals M. <hi>de la Haye,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador made to the Republick of <hi>Venice.</hi> He offer'd the Signiorie, beſides Three Millions in Silver, which were to be paid down, that the King his Maſter ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to prevail with the Grand Signior to grant her Great Advantages, and conclude a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:39221:38"/>ſeparate Treaty of Peace with her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Excluſion of the Emperour and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he King of <hi>Poland,</hi> if ſhe would imploy her Good Offices, as well at <hi>Rome,</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wade the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to reſtore Peace to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taly,</hi> as in other Courts of the Catholic Princes in confederacy againſt <hi>France.</hi> I omit ſeveral private Conferences between his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty and the Venetian Envoy, upon this Subject, before his departure from <hi>Paris,</hi> when he went from thence to reſide in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Court of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How did <hi>Amelot</hi> labour with the laudable Cantons? He diſplay'd all his Eloquence in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Speeches, which he made in their Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, and left nothing undone to advance the King his Maſter's Intereſts. His moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Propoſitions were reduc'd to an Offer of Four Millions and 500000 Livres, to which he addded, the Payment of all their Arrears: All which Advantages, ſaid he farther, would be attended with a perpetual and inviolable Alliance with the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of which the laudable Cantons would be protected at all Times, and the Liberty and Repoſe which they have enjoy'd hitherto would be ſecured from the Attempts of all that ſought their Diſturbance. And all that the King demanded for ſo many Favours, was only that they ſhould be Mediators for a Peace.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:39221:39"/>
            <p>Let us proceed to the fourth Reaſon that engages <hi>France</hi> to ſue for a Peace, which is the low Eſtate of her Exchequer, and the miſerable Condition to which the People are reduc'd. And to be fully ſatisfied in this particular, there needs no more then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, That the moſt Chriſtian King has ſo little ſpar'd his People in Time of Peace, that 'tis no wonder to ſee 'em now reduc'd to utmoſt Miſery. Certain it is, let him put on as good a Face as he pleaſes, that he clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents of a Conduct ſo oppoſite to his real In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts. Good Policy requires that a Prince ſhould diligently labour in ſearch of all the moſt probable ways to procure the flouriſhing Condition of his Kingdom, while a ſound Peace ſecures him from all Attempts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions of his Enemies: To diſcharge his Subjects from the ponderous Burdens, with which they are overwhelm'd during the War; to revoke all Decrees and Declarations that tended to their Ruin; and laſtly, to deliver 'em from all thoſe Burthenſome Impoſitions and chargeable Taxes with which they were oppreſs'd in Time of War; to the end they may have liberty to take Breath, and recover their decay'd Strength, that they may be the better enabl'd to bear new Burthens, when the Exigencies of the State require it.</p>
            <p>Quite the contrary were the Proceedings of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, for no ſooner were the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace, the Treaties of <hi>Aix la Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelle,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:39221:39"/>and <hi>Nimeguen</hi> concluded, but he turns his Arms againſt his own Subjects, and not content with the Devaſtations of all <hi>Europe,</hi> he ranſacks the Bowels of his own Kingdom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd cauſes his People to wiſh a thouſand Times for War rather then Peace; to the end that ſo many miſerable Wretches might live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecure from his Ambitious Tyranny. What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s there to be imagin'd that <hi>France</hi> has left <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndone to ruin his own Subjects? Her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il has exhauſted it ſelf, in Decrees; no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooner is one made publick, but three more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re in the Preſs. The Parliaments and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aign Courts that were formerly Protectors of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he People, and which were erected in the Raigns of this King's Predeceſſors, to ballance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Royal Authority, are now reduc'd to ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> baſe and ſordid Compliance with the Prince, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they only ſit to conſent to, and authorize <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is incroachments upon the People.</p>
            <p>The Farmers, and they who have manag'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Publick Treaſure, what have they left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>one, what Artifices have they not made uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f to draw all the Mony of the Kingdom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the King's Coffers? Have we not ſeen a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olbert</hi> almoſt murder himſelf by tormenting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Brains in finding out a thouſand Tricks to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>educe the People to utmoſt Beggary? That Great Man was the Object of Court Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the Abomination of the People. Nor can I here forbear to recite what one Day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e anſwer'd his Majeſty, upon occaſion of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39221:40"/>ſome new Impoſts that were going to be laid upon his Subjects. For upon the King's tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, That ſuch Exactions would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the People to cry out, meerly for Wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and finding themſelves utterly unable to pay their Aſſeſſments, for that no body could pay who had it not. <hi>O, Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are like a Sack of Flower, the more yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhake it, the more Meal comes forth.</hi> Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it were, both that Miniſter, they that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded, and they that follow'd him in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> management of the Finances, underſtood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> well to ſqueez the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereas Thirty Millions was the higheſt Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to which the Revenue of the Crown amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed formerly, they have rais'd it to above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hundred and threeſcore. We muſt not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore think it ſtrange to ſee that Monarchy op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt as now it is, and the People reduc'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> utmoſt Miſery.</p>
            <p>Beſides all theſe ways, the moſt Chriſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King ſtill puts in practiſe a great number <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> others, which have equally contributed to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ruin of his Subjects; ſuch are his Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Soldiers, Creations of New Offices and ſuppreſſing of others; his pretended Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of the <hi>Huguenot</hi> Hereſie; and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pious Foundations, of which the Kingdom i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> full. His ſordid Compliance with the Monk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Clergy, who poſſeſſing the faireſt Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Realm, have heap'd up vaſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Riches, to the impoveriſhment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:39221:40"/>the meaner ſort, who ſubſiſt only by their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>our and Induſtry. His prodigious Expences <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> building Royal Houſes, and erecting ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uous Monuments to his future Fame. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt Treaſures he has waſted in bringing Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers into Places in deſpite of Mountains, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lid Oppoſitions of Nature, which he has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t through, and Valleys which he has fill'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; all which coſt <hi>France</hi> ſeveral Millions, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rty Thouſand of her beſt Men. We may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to all this, the joining of two Seas, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Royal Canal, in which hard Labours the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing ſacrific'd the ſame number of his ſelect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Subjects. The enhauncing and abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent of Mony, which has ruin'd Trade, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ck'd his People to the laſt drop of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ood. The vaſt number of Forts and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſes which he has built and rais'd upon all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Frontiers of the Kingdom, which has coſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m immenſe Sums. The Penſions which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s paid in all the Courts of <hi>Europe</hi> to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>liances, or for the maintenance of his Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ries, which coſts him ſeveral Millions, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e keeping afoot near two hundred thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en in time of Peace, and 400000 in time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ar; the vaſt Sums which he expends in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ring out great Fleets, beſides what his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>zins of Ammunition and Proviſion upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ontiers coſt him. All this, I ſay, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tes to the Ruin of <hi>France,</hi> and to reduce it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that deplorable Condition wherein we find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at this day.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:39221:41"/>
            <p>Let it be as it will, the moſt Chriſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King having conſum'd the moſt ſolid part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Crown Demeſnes, in ſo many extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant ways of Expence, it may be ſaid, Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he has acted like thoſe unwary Gameſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> who, having undone themſelves by Play <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know not where to betake themſelves to ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more. But this Prince is not only contente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to have plaid away his own Revenues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> has alſo gam'd away the Eſtates of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and by that means has reduc'd <hi>Fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to thoſe Extremities which are enough to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it. So that 'tis no wonder to ſee Fami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rage within his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. might hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiſh'd, that his Father <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Dagobert</hi> the 'Leventh King of <hi>Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had bin ſo pious, or rather a Perſon of ſo mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Fore-ſight, as to have cover'd the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> St. <hi>Denis</hi> with Silver; to the end, that afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he had drein'd his Exchequer, he might hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had the ſame ſhift at a Pinch, as <hi>Clovis,</hi> the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Dagobert</hi> had, who uncovered the Church and made uſe of the Mony to ſave <hi>Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which then began to be afflicted with a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> terrible Dearth. But <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and <hi>Lewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> XIII. had ſo much Work upon their Hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that their Reigns might well be ſaid, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rather Iron then Silver Reigns; and that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were ſo far from having any Overplus's to la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out upon <hi>Dagobert</hi>'s pious uſes, that they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> forc'd to borrow, to ſupply the Exigencies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the State.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:39221:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. was the Prince who of all the Kings of <hi>France</hi> poſſeſs'd the vaſteſt heap of Trea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure, and who beheld himſelf the moſt puiſſant of all his Predeceſſors, by the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Improvement of his Finances and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enues. To be convinc'd of this, there needs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o more but to conſider, That the Revenues of the Crown hardly mounted to 16 Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Reigns of the <hi>Valois</hi>'s. In <hi>Henry</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>V.'s time, they aſcanded to Thirty. <hi>Richlieu</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. rais'd 'em to Forty five, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd after him <hi>Mazarine</hi> advanc'd 'em to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove ſixty: Which was nothing to what they are mounted at preſent; for, according to an exact Computation, <hi>Colbert</hi> and the reſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Publicans and Sinners, have advanc'd 'em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o above a hundred and fifty Millions. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Treaſures of this Monarch were more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmenſe, his Ambition was alſo proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble, and if they have bin ſo far from being ſufficient to ſatisfie it, that he has bin alſo fain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſacrifize the Eſtates of the Church, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Spoils of the Altars, after he has laid Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſts upon all things elſe imaginable, he muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e forc'd, at length, to lay a ſwinging Tex upon Urine, as formerly <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> did.</p>
            <p>An unfortunate Gameſter, after he has loſt all, endeavours to recover himſelf by all the ways he can imagin, and managing the Cards or the Dice by himſelf in his own Hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hinks himſelf at length of playing ſoul.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:39221:42"/>Thus the King of <hi>France,</hi> having ruin'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, his People and his Kingdoms, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudently engaging himſelf in a burthenſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> War, and which having been proſperous a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the beginning, has prov'd fatal to him in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> end, endeavours to get himſelf out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bryars as well as he can. To which purpoſe he offers Peace to the Princes of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, and ſets all Springs at work to brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Union. He makes 'em Propoſals ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous and full of Deluſion; what he offer to day, he revokes to morrow. He order Cardinal <hi>Fourbin</hi> to tell the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> That he is ready to lay down Arms, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enter into a Negotiation with the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Princes; but firſt, there muſt be a ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for King <hi>James</hi> agreed upon.</p>
            <p>To the Northern Crowns his Embaſſador<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> talk another ſort of Language, and tell 'em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> That as to the Affairs of <hi>England,</hi> in regard that Royal Majeſty appears to be wounded in the Perſon of King <hi>James,</hi> he makes no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> and the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, will take it upon 'em to propoſe ſome Expedient to determin that Difference. As to the Court of <hi>Vienna,</hi> 'tis about ten Months ſince, that he made Propoſals of Peace to his Imperial Majeſty, quite different from thoſe that appear'd in his Manifeſto publiſh'd upon the <hi>Rhine.</hi> There is not any one of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Princes or States, to whom he has not offer'd Propoſals altogether different from
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:39221:42"/>thoſe which he now propounds. Witneſs his Temptations to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> firſt by <hi>Chanlais,</hi> then by <hi>Catinat,</hi> and then by other Miniſters.</p>
            <p>As to the States General of the United Provinces, <hi>France</hi> made 'em Propoſals, firſt by <hi>Oxeſterne,</hi> formerly the Swediſh Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or, who had two Audiences to that purpoſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſides the Propoſals made 'em by M. <hi>Lenthe</hi> the Daniſh Envoy. She has obſerv'd the ſame conduct at the Court of <hi>England,</hi> where M. <hi>Scheel</hi> now talks at another rate. Several other Projects have been preſented at the Courts of all the reſt of the Confederate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, wherein there is nothing ſolid or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. ſhich is a convincing Proof that the moſt Chriſtian King ſeeks only to draw the Confederates into a Negotiation, to obtain a Ceſſation of Arms on purpoſe to amuſe 'em, while he on the other ſide aſſays by more powerful efforts to ruin their Union.</p>
            <p>And this is <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV's foul Play, and the compaſs which he fetches to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>attain his Ends, and diſintangle himſelf out of the Nooſe that hampers him, by ſaving, if poſſible, the beſt part of his Conqueſts, and delivering his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh'd Dominions from the ponderous Burthens which they groan under. And now 'tis for the Confederate Princes to conſider what they have to do, and not to ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be deluded by the falſe and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſhifts of <hi>France,</hi> and ſeriouſly to reflect
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:39221:43"/>upon the fatal Misfortunes that will infallibly attend the concluſion of a diſadvantagiou Peace, if lending their Ears to the Offers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>France,</hi> they neglect the faireſt opportunit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that ever was, to humble that haughty and perfidious Potentate, at a time when he beg for Peace, and when there needs no more the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two Campaigns to obtain all the Advantage<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which they can expect to reap from thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Perſeverance. Which is ſo much the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Important, as being the reaſon that has arm'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all <hi>Europe</hi> againſt him, and occaſion'd tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> auguſt and potent Confederacy of ſo many juſtly incens'd Princes, and who are equally intereſted therein.</p>
            <p>But what Aſſurances ſhall they have tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Peace which the moſt Chriſtian King now propoſes, ſhall not be violated like th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace, and the Treaties of <hi>Aix <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chapelle</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen?</hi> How can they rely upon the Oath of a Prince, who acknowledges no other Law then that of his Ambition and Will? At the Peace of <hi>Arras, lip</hi> the Good, Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> not being willing to truſt <hi>Charles</hi> VII. who had brok'n his word in ſeveral other Treaties, was deſirous that the laſt Article of the Treaty ſhould run in theſe words: <hi>That the King for aſſurance of the obſervation and full performance of the ſaid Treaty, ſhould deliver it ſeal'd by the Princes of his Blood, the Grandees of the Kingdom, and the principal Men of the chief Cities; and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:39221:43"/>that in caſe of any Breach, thoſe Princes and Lords ſhould be abſolv'd from their Oaths of Fidelity toward the King, and be oblig'd to ſerve the Duke againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Precautions of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> upon that occaſion, might in ſome meaſure ſerve as a Garranty to ſecure the obſervance of <hi>Charles</hi> VII's Word and Oath. But it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be conſider'd, That the condition of the Grandees of the Kingdom, was not then the ſame as now it is. <hi>Charles</hi> VII. wanted a great deal of being ſo well belov'd, and ſo much fear'd by the People and Nobility of <hi>France,</hi> as <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. at this day. The ways which he has taken to gain the Affection of his Subjects are quite different. Formerly a little thing would have open'd a wide Gate to Faction and Revolt, and incens'd the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees and Lords of the Kingdom to take Arms: But now the Caſe is alter'd. The King has reduc'd 'em all equally to ſuch a dependance upon him, that no Body dares ſtir; and it would be in vain for the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Princes to think of laying the foundation of a ſolid and laſting Peace upon any ſuch Article, in imitation of the Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For proof of this we may obſerve, that ſince the beginning of this Reign, looking backward as far as the King's Minority, <hi>France</hi> has no longer car'd to be ſenſible or take notice of the Troubles that had lacerated
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:39221:44"/>her very Bowels: So that notwithſtanding all the Efforts that were usd to re-kindle the ſame Sparks, it was impoſſible to bring it to paſs. To which, it may be ſaid that <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> and the Miniſters that ſucceeded him, as alſo the King himſelf, who is ſharp-ſighted enough, did not contribute a little by means of their good management at the beginning. And in regard the People are ignorant in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and for that it is impoſſible for 'em to dive into the ſecrets of the Cabinet, 'twas an eaſie thing for that Monarch, being ſo good a <hi>Matchiavilian</hi> as he is, to reduce his Subjects under that Bondage, wherein we now behold 'em. He eaſily brought it to paſs, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving 'em of all the means that might prove a Bait to Inſurrection.</p>
            <p>Therefore, it behoves the Confederate Princes to take another courſe, which is, to oppoſe him with a puiſſant Force proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his own, and to tire him out by a prolongation of the War, which will at length enforce him, when throughly debilitated and brought upon his laſt Legs, to reſtore to every one their Rights, and what he has uſurp'd by breach of Treaties, and no leſs treacherous in obſervance of his word.</p>
            <p>As often as I revolve in my mind the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels which <hi>Lewis</hi> XII. had with <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and compare the Genius's of thoſe two Princes one with the other, as well as their Conduct, I cannot forbear to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:39221:44"/>it to the Conteſts at this preſent between <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and the Confederate Princes. For in all the Treaties that <hi>Lewis</hi> made with <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> the latter was always too hard for the former: And it may be ſaid, That of the Princes that ever reign'd, there never was one more perfidious, or who more gloriouſly vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Diſplay of his Diſhoneſty; as may appear by the Reply which he made his Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, who telling his Maſter how <hi>Lewis</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd extreamly of his having deceiv'd him twice. <hi>Twice!</hi> reply'd <hi>Ferdinand, By God he lies like a Tooth-drawer, I have cheated him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ten times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am perſuaded that the moſt Chriſtian King has out-done <hi>Ferdinand</hi> in point of Knavery: So that if the Confederates ſhould reproach him with having twice deceiv'd 'em, he might truly anſwer, that he had deceiv'd 'em as oft as he concluded Treaties with 'em. So that the Confederate Princes have no more to do then to conſider, how little Ground they have to depen'd upon that Monarch, who boaſts the Trophies of his Perfidiouſneſs no leſs then <hi>Ferdinand.</hi> But the Friends of <hi>France</hi> will anſwer, That <hi>Lewis</hi> XII. was as little ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in violating his word, in his Treaties with <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperor; witneſs the Treaties of <hi>Trent</hi> and <hi>Blois.</hi> Which if it be true, and that Princes violate their Words and Oaths as ſoon as they have pledg'd and ſworn 'em, to what purpoſe do Treaties ſerve? We
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:39221:45"/>muſt ſay, as <hi>Silius</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hannibal,</hi> That <hi>Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Juſtice hang at the point of the Sword,</hi> and that prevailing Power is the only Law among the great ones: And thus you ſee a wide Gate ſet open for Plunder and Robbery, and there Remains no more for us to do, but to prepare our ſelves for open and perpetual War, and the continual ſhedding of Blood, with as much Cruelty and Barbariſm, as Beaſts of Prey: According to the words of <hi>Seneca,</hi> ſpeaking of unjuſt Wars. I can ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, 'tis not only a piece of Cruelty, but the natural Inclination of a Savage Beaſt, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in nothing but Blood. We may call it a turning of the Brains topſie-turvie, or a ſort of Madneſs, for there are ſeveral kinds of it; Tho' none more viſible then that which tranſports Men to Murder and Butchery.</p>
            <p>We may aver, without wronging the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, that <hi>Seneca</hi> learns him a good Leſſon in this Place, and not only him but all other Ambitious Princes. Nor is <hi>Seneca</hi> the only Abhorrer of theſe abominable Principles. <hi>That Man,</hi> ſays <hi>Ariſtotle, muſt needs be lookt upon as very cruel, who makes his Friends his Enemies,</hi> out of a Deſire only to make War. In like manner ſays <hi>Dio</hi> the <hi>Pruſiean, To be prone to War and Combat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Cauſe, is a pure Madneſs that ſeeks Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief for Miſchief's ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However it be, this is certain, that the moſt Chriſtian King himſelf being the Author
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39221:45"/>of all the Calamities and Misfortunes that at preſent turmoyle <hi>Europe,</hi> as well as his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, among whom we may number <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburgh,</hi> who may be call'd his Right Hand, and the Perſon who infuſes into him a good part of theſe Cruelties which his Armies commit, will be no leſs reſponſible before God, then if he ſhould imbrue his Hands in the ſame Maſſakers. Let him give out as long as he pleaſes, by his Miniſters and Emiſſaries in all the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> That he burns with a Deſire to ſtop the Bleeding Veins of of ſo many Innocents, who ſhed their Blood in this cruel War: Let him publiſh by ſound of Trumpet, by Heralds at Arms, in all the chief Streets of his Capital City, his eager Paſſion to reſtore Peace to his Subjects: Let him order the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> to order the tiring all the Saints in Heaven, with his Forty Hours prayers; Let him weary the Holy Father with Importunities, to mediate an Accommodation between him and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Princes, as formerly did <hi>Paul</hi> III. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Charles</hi> V. and <hi>Francis</hi> I.</p>
            <p>We muſt anſwer him in a Word, that 'tis not his Grief for the Sufferings of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> that inclines him to a Peace, but his eager deſire to diſſolve the Union of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Princes, whoſe power infuſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him Fears of dreadful Conſequence; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, after he has recover'd Strength, to recommence the War, and plague all <hi>Europe</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:39221:46"/>with more Miſchiefs in the midſt of Peace then in the heat of blody War.</p>
            <p>If this Monarch have now more pious and equitable Sentiments, and ſuch as are truly different from thoſe which he had when he concluded the Three ſo often-mention'd Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, together with the Truce for Twenty Years, let him make 'em appear by the Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all that he has uſurp'd ſince the firſt Peace concluded in the Iſland of <hi>Pheſants.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Lawyers affirm, That he is a public Robber, who being demanded, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he detains the Poſſeſſion of ſuch or ſuch a thing, has no other reaſon to give then only becauſe he poſſeſſes it. To which we may add that Saying of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſpeaking of thoſe who adviſe War, <hi>That they very ſeldom take any heed whether it be Juſt and Lawful to reduce their Neighbours under the Yoak of Bondage, who never gave 'm any Cauſe; or to oppreſs thoſe, who never did 'em any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should the Queſtion be put to <hi>France,</hi> by what Rights ſhe now poſſeſſes ſo many Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and ſeparate Dominions, of which ſhe has deſpoil'd ſo many ſeveral Soveraign Princes? It would not ſuffice her to allege her chimerical Rights of Reunion, Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ence, pumpt from the hollow Noddle of ſome old Advocate of the Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Paris,</hi> more fit to be derided then to be the Ground of any ſerious Conteſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39221:46"/>important Matters of Fact muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by ſound, ſolid and undeniable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. But if you can but get <hi>France</hi> from thence, as out of her Fortreſs, in regard ſhe had no other Reaſon to give, ſhe muſt be conſtrain'd to acknowledge, that ſhe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes 'em, becauſe ſhe poſſeſſes 'em. So that is not this a perfect Robbery and a manifeſt U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation of her Neighbour's Rights? and is there any Wrong done her in demanding Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution? Ought ſhe not to be contented with her having enjoy'd 'em ſo many Years, and to have all-a-long receiv'd the Revenues which amount to immenſe Sums? It may be thought alſo, that the Princes of the League would do her a great Favour, if they diſcharge her at ſo cheap a rate, as the reſtoring 'em in the ſame Condition as actually now they are, which, without Contradiction, is far worſe then what they were in when ſhe firſt ſeiz'd upon 'em. For examgle, <hi>Alſatia, Franche Conte,</hi> the Dutchies of <hi>Burgundy, Lorraine</hi> and <hi>Bar;</hi> of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> and <hi>Deux Ponts,</hi> the County of <hi>Chini,</hi> the Principality of <hi>Orange,</hi> part of <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Fland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> all which ſhe has uſurp'd and annex'd to the Crown. No Body can be ignorant that all theſe were opulent and flouriſhing Countries under the Dominion of their Lawful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, whereas at preſent they are impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh'd, and reduc'd to utmoſt miſery. Could a true Computation be made of the Wealth
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:39221:47"/>which they abounded in before they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded by <hi>France,</hi> I am perſwaded there would not now be found ſo much Mony in all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as one ſingle Principality was worth at that Time. So that if <hi>France</hi> be diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for making Reſtitution of 'em in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition, ſhe muſt needs be a prodigious Gainer, conſidering that ſhe goes clear away with all the Spoils, of which ſhe has ſtript thoſe Provinces to their Skins, to erect a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſance always formidable to her Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, it may be ſaid, that if the Confederates enforce that Crown to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member from her Dominions ſo many potent Principalities, and ſo many lovely Acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they may juſtly promiſe to themſelves a juſt and durable Peace, by diſabling her to extend her ambitious Incroachments, as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſhe has done. There is no doubt but the Predeceſſors of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great would shave been as active and as troubleſome to their Neighbours as he, had they had the ſame Force and the ſame Treaſures. The Deſire of growing Great is natural to all Sovereigns, and it is look'd upon as a Noble Paſſion, when it is ſufficiently ſupported to carry on Great Enterprizes, and is attended with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity. So that if the Raigns of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. were not ſo fortunate and flouriſhing as that of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. 'twas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wanted Power, and becauſe their
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:39221:47"/>Revenues were ſo ſmall, that they could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring into the Field an Army of above 40 or 50000 Men, whereas <hi>France,</hi> under this Ragin, has extended her Limits ſo far as ſhe has done by the vaſt Augmentation of her Forces, and prodigious Advancemen of her Revenus; to which her Violation of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties has greatly contributed. She finds her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf enlarg'd by a great number of Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Earldoms, Principalities, Lordſhips, Signiories and Territories ſufficient altogether to compoſe a Kingdom as vaſt and of as large an extent as ancient <hi>France;</hi> nay, tho you ſhould conſider it as it was before the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace.</p>
            <p>'Tis Time then, moſt Serene Confederate Princes, to bethink your ſelves of preſcribing Bounds to this ambitious Puiſſance, ſuch as may ſecure your Liberty, your Repoſe, and the Welfare of your Dominions. You know full well, what your ſtaying ſo long has coſt ye, and paſt Experience ought to inſtruct ye, that you have no time to loſe; and that if you let ſlip this favourable Opportunity, which Fortune has put into your Hands, ſuch another may not ſuddenly return. The Marquiſs of <hi>Louvois</hi> told the King, ſome Months before his Death, <hi>That he foreſaw this War would be like the Preceding: That your Projects and your Enterprizes would vaniſh in Smoak; That Miſunderſtanding began to get footing among ye; that one Campaign
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:39221:48"/>more would ſhatter the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and that there wanted nothing but the Loſs of a Battle, to make a ſecond Peace of</hi> Nimeguen. That is to ſay, a Peace both Glorious and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious for <hi>France,</hi> and unfortunate to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates. This Miniſter, zealous for his Maſter's Intereſts, grounded his Arguments and Conjectures upon the ſmall Reſiſtance which you made till now; which occaſion'd the loſs of ſeveral Battels, and the taking of ſeveral conſiderable Towns. And, to ſpeak, as we find things, it was not greatly for the Honour of ſo many Princes as the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy conſiſs of, that only <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> have fought effectually a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Two Potentates have done every thing, have paid every thing, have ſupply'd every thing: So that 'is no wonder if they have obtain'd ſignal Advantages. At the ſame Time <hi>France</hi> aſſails ye on every ſide; Her Armies are early in the Field; they ravage your Territories, and carry all before 'em with Fire, with Sword and Deſolation, while you remain immoveable in Winter-Quarters, till the Enemy has made himſelf Maſter of the moſt Advantagious Poſts, and conſum'd your Forrage.</p>
            <p>I bury in ſilence a great number of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and Failings which King <hi>William</hi> has endeavour'd to repair with indefatigable Pains and Induſtry. 'Tis to that great Prince, to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:39221:48"/>whom all <hi>Europe</hi> is at this Day heholding for the happy condition of her Affairs, which put all the Confederates in hopes of a ſpeedy and ſolid Peace. It is only to be wiſh'd that the Zeal of that undaunted Monarch were well ſeconded, and that all the Confederate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and States would puſh on their utmoſt Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, towards putting a final End to ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious an Enterprize, after which ſo many People, under Oppreſſion, ſo earneſtly pant.</p>
            <p>Now, to be convinc'd that there needs no more then the good fortune of one Compaign, ſucceſsful to the Confederates, to obtain of <hi>France</hi> what has been uſurp'd ſince the <hi>Pyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean</hi> Treaty, let us only conſider her Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and her Condeſcenſions to obtain a Peace. Having hitherto ſown, in vain, her Treaſures in all the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe the Neutrality of ſeveral Members of the Confederacy, or the Mediation of the Northern Crowns, and other States and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, devoted to her Intereſts; finding that all this produc'd nothing, ſhe flatter'd her ſelf, as her laſt Remedy, that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> would have Authority enough to awe the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Princes into an Accommodation. To that purpoſe ſhe left nothing omitted to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Favour of that Court; and it may be ſaid that her Sedulities were not Fruitleſs on that ſide, and that it was none of the Holy Fathers Fault, if the Emperor and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:39221:49"/>the Catholick King did not abandon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cauſe, to make a ſeparate Peace.</p>
            <p>It had bin well for <hi>France,</hi> that the preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pope had had the good luck or the Genius o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Clement</hi> VIII. at the Peace of <hi>Vervin,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in 1598. That Holy Father preſs'd ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> importunately upon <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and <hi>Philip</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he perſwaded thoſe Two Princes at length into a Reconciliation, and to reſtore Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility to <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> Nevertheleſs it was not procur'd without a world of Toyl and Difficulty, witneſs the extraordinary Pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the Popes Legate, Cardinal <hi>Alexander d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Medicis</hi> took, who was ſent to <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and had not that Cardinal bin as cunning as he was, he had never ſucceeded, nor done his Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as he did, with that Prince. Nor was the Reverend Father, Friar <hi>Bonaventure Calatagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone,</hi> General of the <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Order, leſs dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous in perſwading Prince <hi>Albert,</hi> Archduke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and Nephew to <hi>Philip.</hi> II. So that the Holy Father wrought ſo effectually by the means of thoſe two great Men, that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded both Crowns to lay down their Arms, and ſo ſecond the Repoſe and Tranquility of <hi>Europe,</hi> which was almoſt in the ſame Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as now it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> having always obſerv'd that the Popes had bin always the Sovereign Umpires and Arbitrators of the Quarrels between the Two Houſes, could not take a more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious and more favourable Courſe then
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:39221:49"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow ſhe did. But, as we have already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erv'd, 'twas not ſufficient for <hi>France</hi> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>econcil d to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> by ſacrificing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o her all her Reſentments, which ſeem'd to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end to a perſonal Enmity and Diſobedience, which <hi>France</hi> had diſplay'd to all the World with ſo much Pride and Haughtineſs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y this means to have induc'd her to eſpouſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Intereſts; there was a neceſſity of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, that ſhould have met in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the preſent <hi>Pope,</hi> a cunning Dexterity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike that of <hi>Clement</hi> VIII. and <hi>Paul</hi> III. who Mediated the Peace between <hi>Charles</hi> V. and <hi>Francis</hi> I.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Clement</hi> was put to ſo much Trouble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could pacifie the Troubles that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and <hi>Philip</hi> II. Irreconcilable, Pope <hi>Paul</hi> had much more to do with <hi>Charles</hi> V. and <hi>Francis</hi> I. who being come to <hi>Nice,</hi> where Pope <hi>Paul</hi> III. expeced 'em to put an end to their Differences, as a Common Father and Mediator, all that the Holy Father who was the moſt Perſpicatious and Politic Prince of his Age, could do, was to make thoſe two Monarchs agree upon a Truce for Ten Years, without ſeeing each other; it being impoſſible for him to perſwade 'em to a final Peace. So that one may ſafely ſay, that Affairs are at preſent in the ſame poſture, and that there appears but very little hope for the Moſt Chriſtian King to expect a Peace by the way of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Union of the Confederate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:39221:50"/>is knit ſo faſt, that 'tis in vain for him to think to diſſolve it by any Intrigues of the Spiritual Court. As Crafty as the Cardinals <hi>Fourbin</hi> and <hi>d' Estrees</hi> are, and whatever Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices they make uſe of, we do not find they have made any progreſs as yet. So that <hi>France</hi> having nothing to truſt to but her Arms, of neceſſity ſhe muſt renew her preparations for the War, or propound more Honourable and Advantageous Offers in order to a Peace, then thoſe already preſented by the Miniſters of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Confederate Princes will never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any Treaty that is not attended with the Reſtitution of all that <hi>France</hi> has Uſurp'd ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty. Let her thunder out her Reſentment in the rage and fury of new Cruelties: Let her Burn and lay all Waſte before her: Let her do all the Miſchief that formerly was practis'd by <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Bald,</hi> Sur-named the <hi>Terrible,</hi> with a deſign to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by Force what he cannot obtain by Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Means. Let him make his Proteſtations in all the Courts of Europe, that he is ready to lay down his Arms: Let him proclaim as loud as he pleaſes by the Mouths of his Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, the ſincerity of his Intentions: Let him exalt himſelf in Promiſes, and with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Rodomantadoes ſound forth the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages which he offers the Confederates; All this will never inveagle 'em to accept of a Treaty.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:39221:50"/>
            <p>The Confederate Princes are now reſolv'd to imitate the Conduct of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. toward <hi>Philip</hi> II. For <hi>Henry</hi> having too often expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd how little all the Promiſes of the Spaniſh Monarch were to be rely'd upon, would never enter into any Negotiation, till he had made Reſtitution of all his Conqueſts; and order'd him to be told, that when he had reſtor'd back all that he had taken from him, then ſhould the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſee what he would do. The Confederate Princes have both rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and are likewiſe in a condition to hold the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Noſe to the ſame Grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. When he has reſtor'd to every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſon what he has wreſted from 'em by Invaſion; the Eſtates and Fortreſſes of which he has deſpoiled ſeveral Sovereign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Then the Allies will enter into a Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the end they may all together agree upon the Means the moſt effectual to procure a ſolid and laſting Peace.</p>
            <p>If they delay to enter into a Negotiation till <hi>France</hi> ſhall make a Previous Offer of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring all ſhe has won fince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, there is no queſtion but ſhe will do as ſhe did at the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> that is to ſay, ſhe will commit more Havoc and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties then in the greateſt heat of War, on purpoſe to make 'em haſten the concluſion of the Treaty, and be more willing to grant her Demands. This Condct of hers is ſo much the more Advantageous, becauſe ſhe knows by
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:39221:51"/>Experience, that her talking of Peace, was wont to lull the Confederates aſleeep, while on the other ſide Miſunderſtanding crept in among 'em; beſides that, they were willing to leſſent their Forces at a time when it became 'em rather to redouble their Efforts.</p>
            <p>If the King of <hi>France</hi> had the good luck to Succeed, and that he effectually perſwaded the Confederate Princes to accept his Offers, He had no ſmall reaſon at that imte to boaſt his having reſtor'd Peace to <hi>Europen,</hi> but they might well cry out with <hi>Horace</hi> for all that,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quid dignum tanto feret hic Promiſſor hiatu,</l>
               <l>Parturiunt Montes naſcetur Ridiculus Mus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Andbe had likewiſe as much reaſon to ſay, that he had the honour to make all the Confederates draw their Swords, and to Diſarm 'em when they had done; and that that ſame Potent League, ſufficient to have made the French Monarchy Tremble, and reduce her to her ancient Bounds, did nothing more then only Forge the Shackles themſelves, with which <hi>France</hi> intended to have bound 'em to a more cruel Slavery then what they had endur'd before.</p>
            <p>To be convinc'd of this, there needs no more but to conſider, that all that <hi>France</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to reſtore to the Confederates, may be re-taken by her Arms in leſs then one Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pain, ſo ſoon as the Confederates ſhould have
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:39221:51"/>laid down their Arms and Disbanded their forces. There's no neceſſity for me to enlarge upon the Proof of this: 'Tis ſufficient to ſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he King of <hi>France</hi> has no other Aim, then to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>evive his old Maxims, preſently after the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Peace. And indeed 'tis a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for an Unlimited Prince to ſet Bounds to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Deſigns, and to root out of his Heart, the principles which Ambition and Avarice, have Planted there with ſo much Induſtry even from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is tender Youth. And therefore we muſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>buſe our ſelves; ſo long as <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great continues Great, as being ſurrounded with ſuch a real and effectual Power as he now Poſſeſſes, which may be ſaid to be the higheſt degree of Exaltation and Grandeur to which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Prince can attain, he will always give Laws to <hi>Europe,</hi> and all the reſt of the Princes muſt depend upon him in ſuch a manner, as never to be able to Affranchiſe themſelves but by his Downfall.</p>
            <p>Let 'em Upbraid as much as they pleaſe <hi>Charles</hi> the Groſs with his want of Sincerity during the whoſe courſe of his Reign, and the paltry Artifices he made uſe of to rid himſelf of his Enemies; he never alter'd his Conduct nor his Maxims; ſo long as he had the Power in his Hands, he was always the ſame; and it may be ſaid, that he never began to live in Repoſe and to become wiſe, till he was Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh'd into a Village of <hi>Swabia,</hi> with a very mean Penſion, where he Died for Grief. <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thair</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:39221:52"/>the Son of <hi>Lewis Oultremer</hi> the XXXIV King of <hi>France,</hi> was a Prince the moſt Perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and the moſt Turbulent that ever aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Throne of the French Monarchy; and as he liv'd, ſo he dy'd, and retain'd his abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Principle to his Death. So that we may ſafely ſay, That ſo long as the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King continues as Potent as he is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, he will never ſuffer his Neighbours to be at Quiet; and the Confederate Princes muſt be always preparing themſelves for new Combuſtions, after the concluſion of a Peace. Which will be fo far from leſſening his Forces, that it will acquire him new degrees of Glory and Grandeur.</p>
            <p>Since then 'tis ſo abſolutely neceſſary to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the preſent Offers of the Moſt Chriſtian King, and that there is no other way to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a firm Peace, but by the continuance of a brisk War, in order to bring down the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of this Monarch, there is no time to loſe; within a MOnth or ſix Weeks, his Armies will be in the Field, and if we may believe him, he will be no longer bound to ſtand to his Royal Word, which he gave the <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>March.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> begins to Liquor his Boots, and is preparing in earneſt to ſhew us ſome new Trick of his Necroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And this ſame Marſhal, whom the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was wont to call <hi>L'Enfant perdu,</hi> or a <hi>Child of the forlorn Hope,</hi> in referrence to his turbulent and ſanguinary Genius, has promis'd
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:39221:52"/>his Majeſty, that tho' it coſt him his Life, he will make him Maſter this Campaign, either of <hi>Liege</hi> or <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> or at the worſt of a ſecond Field-Victory, no leſs Glorious then that of <hi>Landen,</hi> out of a confidence, that one of theſe Events will force the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates in deſpight of their Teeths, to accept the Peace which he Offers.</p>
            <p>But to return to the Battle of <hi>Landen;</hi> I cannot forbear to write a pleaſant Paſſage, which is reported of the Marſhal. So ſoon as the Battle was over, ſeeing himſelf inviron'd with a crowd of Lieutenant Generals, Camp-Marſhals, Brigadiers, Major-Generals and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers of the Army, who came all to Congratulate him for the ſignal Victory he had own, <hi>Ha! Boys,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>How ſhall we call this Battle?</hi> Upon which, while every one ſtood gaping one upon another, not knowing what to Anſwer, and that ſome were of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to call it be the Name of the Place where it was Fought, according to Cuſtom, the Marſhal replied, <hi>No, Gentlemen, we will call it the Bavin-Battle: inſtead of calling it the Battle of</hi> Landen, <hi>we muſt call it the Battle of Bavins.</hi> And indeed he had reaſon enough to call it ſo. However, if he deceiv'd the Confederates, by Attacquing an Army of no more then Forty Thouſand, with another of a Hundred and twenty Thouſand, let him take heed he be not deceiv'd in his turn, if ever he be forc'd to Fight upon equal Terms,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:39221:53"/>as in all probability he may be this very Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign. Nevertheleſs we may be bold to tell him this, That if he acted like a Maſter in the Art of War in time of Fight, he committed the fault of an ignorant Apprentice, in not purſuing his Victory, and reaping no Fruit of ſo much Blood as had been ſhed. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Subject,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boufflers,</hi> another Favourite of the French Monarch, promis'd him Mountains and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and for a greater proof of his Zeal and Devotion to his Majeſty's Service, he has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready caus'd his Sword to be Whetted, and his own and the Arms of the French Guards, together with the Flambeaux for the Houſe-Burners, to be Bleſs'd by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris;</hi> with a reſolution to fight like a <hi>Termagaunt,</hi> and to lay Waſte all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him with Fire and Sword. <hi>Catinat</hi> alſo no leſs famous for the Lawrels he gather'd in the Field of <hi>Marſaglia,</hi> makes as great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to the King his Maſter; and if his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will believe him, the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> runs a great hazard of loſing the reſt of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and of hearing French <hi>Te Deums</hi> Sung in the Cathedral of <hi>Turin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Dauphin</hi> alſo, who is to Command in <hi>Germany,</hi> if he be not Countermanded, wants neither Courage nor good Will. He has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſignal proofs of both upon ſeveral Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and if we may believe him, <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Baden</hi>'s Buſineſs is only to ſeek for an <hi>Aſylum</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:39221:53"/>and a Camp that may ſecure him from the loſs of a Battle, like that of the laſt Campaign. And as an accumulation to the Vauntings of ſo many Hero's that labour by Concert for the Honour of their Prince, and to draw <hi>Dun</hi> out of the Mire, there wants nothing but a ſecond <hi>Smyrna</hi> Fleet, and <hi>Tourville</hi> Admiral of a French Navy, to render him as Glorious by Sea, as the other Generals pretend to be by Land.</p>
            <p>We are then in great expectation of ſome extraordinary Event, which muſt decide the good or bad Fortune of ſo many Princes, which the Moſt Chriſtian King has enforc'd to betake themſelves to Arms. And the Confederate Princes are ſo much the rather enclin'd to terminate the Differences by the Sword, becauſe they find it impoſſible to obtain by any other means an Accomodation with <hi>France.</hi> Which is no more then what the moſt Chriſtian King has made moſt clearly apparent, by the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Propoſals offer'd by the Miniſters of the Northern Crowns. So that War being indiſpenſably neceſſary, it behoves 'em to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for it in good earneſt.</p>
            <p>If we may believe the News that is brought us from ſome Perſons reſiding in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> 'tis ſaid that his Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Majeſty was in a pelting Chafe to hear that his Offers were rejected with ſo much Scorn; and there was not a day paſt over his
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:39221:54"/>Head, that he did not confer with Marſhal <hi>de Luxemburg,</hi> about what Enterprize was fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be undertaken, and where it was moſt proper to open the Campaign. For the King well knowing of what Importance it would be to his Affairs, would fain have ſomething done Remarkable to raiſe the drooping hope of his dejected People, and which might a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame time uphold the Reputation of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Arms, and conſtrain the Confederates a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> length to accept the Peace which he Offer 'em. All theſe Conſiderations put him to a great Nonplus. To begin in <hi>Flanders</hi> with the Siege of ſome Place of Importance, would not be amiſs; But as ill Luck will have it there are no more <hi>Mons</hi>'s and <hi>Namur</hi>'s to take, there remain two Places only be worthy the Preſenceof ſo great a King; <hi>Liege</hi> and <hi>Maeſtriecht.</hi> But the Cuſtody and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of one of theſe Places, is entruſted with the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and for that <hi>Luxemburg</hi> has had too much experience of the Bravery of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> 'tis not his Opinion that his Majeſty ſhould adventure his Fame and Reputation upon a Siege where he muſt fight againſt whole Armies, of which the Gariſons are Compos'd. So that his Majeſty in all likelyhood will be contented with taking a Journey into <hi>Flanders,</hi> to give his Ladies a little freſh Air; and if he finds no probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of doing any thing conſiderable, he will
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:39221:54"/>return by the way of <hi>Dinant,</hi> under pretence of ſome Indiſpoſition of Body.</p>
            <p>If the Marſhals of <hi>Luxemburg, de Lorge, Catinat</hi> and <hi>Bouflers,</hi> are to be believ'd, there will be ſome ſet-Battles this Year; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was not thought convenient to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any this laſt Winter, for fear of Tyring out the Soldiers, conſidering the need of Freſh Men to ſupport ſo many great Actions. Only the <hi>French</hi> could wiſh their Cavalry were a little more Numerous, and that they could be ſuppli'd with the Horſes which the <hi>Jews</hi> of <hi>Metz</hi> engag'd to procure 'em. But the ſtrict Order taken by the Confederates, was an Invincible Obſtacle which they never expected.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what famous Exploits were deſign'd in the Cabinet at <hi>Verſailles.</hi> But if the Confederate Princes do their Duty, and act, by concert, 'tis in a manner certain, that <hi>France</hi> will only Triumph in Imagination, and that ſhe runs a great hazard of ſeeing her ſelf in as bad or worſe Condition in the end of the Campaign as ſhe was at the Beginning. The Confederates with much more reaſon, hope to Ruin her by prolonging the War, and to enforce her in deſpight of all her Flouriſhes and Bravado's, to Surrender back all her U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations. 'Tis a good Omen for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, that <hi>France</hi> begins the firſt of all to talke of Peace, and that ſhe offers to reſtore ſome part of her Conqueſts. 'Tis a ſign ſhe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:39221:55"/>is weary of the War, and that her Conſcience upbraids her with Perfidiouſneſs, and at the ſame time ordains her to make reſtitution of her Uſurpations, if ſhe intends to be Reconcil'd with her Enemies. As for the Confederates, who are without Reproach in that Particular, they are not yet ſo Harraſs'd by the incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent Neceſſities and fatal Exigencies attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a long War, but that with far leſs Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, they can ſtill maintain their Reſolutions of never hearkning to a Treaty, unleſs that <hi>France</hi> ſubmit to ſurrender whatever ſhe has poſſeſs'd her ſelf of by Invaſion ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="addenda">
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:39221:55"/>
            <head>ADDENDA.</head>
            <p>THAT it is the general Intereſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> to have the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty reſtor'd to its full Force, has been ſhewn at large in the <hi>foregoing</hi> Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but how particularly <hi>England</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in that Reſtitution, is what will appear by the following Reflections; wherein I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſhew that it is particularly both the Intereſt and Honour of this Nation, never to conſent to a <hi>Peace,</hi> till the Affairs of <hi>Europe</hi> be reduc'd to the ſame condition as they were when the <hi>Treaty,</hi> we ſpeak of, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
            <p>'Tis agreed on all hands, That the Peace of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> cannot be laſting and firm, unleſs there be an <hi>Equilibrium</hi> between the two Greateſt Powers: For, when at any Time one prevails over the other, Ambition never wants a Pretence to make War; which, in its conſequence, tho at firſt began only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them Two, yet in the end ſets all the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:39221:56"/>States of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> together by the Ears and involves them in all the Miſeries that attends a moſt barbarous and unmerciful War. So long as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were at the Top of the Wheel, what Troubles, Wars and Misfortunes did they not occaſion in <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> by their fooliſh and immoderate Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to Lord it over all the World beſides And ſince the <hi>French</hi> have ſucceeded them in their Fortunes and Deſigns, what Barbarities, deſolations and Cruelties have we not ſeen and felt? This therefore ſheweth the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity of an <hi>Equilibrum</hi> between <hi>France</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> but the Queſtion is how to come at it.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever will be at the pains to conſider well what has bin ſaid before, muſt agree, That there is no other way left to balance thoſe two Powers, but to revive the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty; which put ſuch reaſonable Bounds to thoſe two contending Empires, that, I dare ſay, it would be very eaſy to preſerve Peace in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> did the Chriſtians but mind their own true Intereſt. But, perhaps, ſome will ſay againſt this; How can you affirm that that Treaty did ſet the Scales even between thoſe two Crowns, ſeeing the <hi>French</hi> are grown ſo powerful ſince that time, and the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> on the other Hand have ſuffer'd ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Loſſes? This is a great Objection, I confeſs indeed, and that which ſeems, at firſt, a <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> that that Treaty was
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:39221:56"/>too advantagious to <hi>France;</hi> yet when it is throughly enquir'd into, it will appear to be very trivial, and of no force at all, as I hope to ſhew before I have done.</p>
            <p>And the better to clear this Difficulty, I ſay, firſt That to pretend to ſet ſuch an exact <hi>Equilibrium</hi> between <hi>France</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> as may infallibly ſecure the Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> without the concurrence of the other States, is a fooliſh and an idle Speculation, and, indeed, an Impoſſibility.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all that we can reaſonably expect, is, to ſet <hi>France</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> in ſuch a condition, that whenever one of them ſhall venture to diſturb the Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> it might be in the power of another State to turn the Scales, and command them to be quiet. And</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſay, That the Treaty concluded at the <hi>Pyrenees,</hi> left <hi>France</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> in ſuch a condition.</p>
            <p>Now to prove this, I have nothing elſe to do, but to ſhew, That there was then ſuch a Power in being, as was able to keep both the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> in Peace, and that was <hi>England.</hi> But to ſet this truth in its full Light, I ſhall only put the Reader in mind of the Cauſes of the Growth of <hi>France,</hi> in which the Author of the foregoing Treatiſe is, in my Opinion, very <hi>defective.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:39221:57"/>
            <p>For tho' the great Ability of their <hi>Miniſters of State,</hi> the good uſe of their <hi>Mony,</hi> and the <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> of their <hi>King,</hi> may have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed very much to theſe <hi>Conqueſts;</hi> yet, after all, they owe more, to ſay not all, to the kindneſs of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. and to the ſupine careleſneſs of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> This will appear the more viſible, if we conſider the happy Circumſtances that King <hi>Charles</hi> was in upon his <hi>Reſtoration.</hi> The Effeminacy, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xury, and other Vices which have bin ſince ſo common amonſt us, were then unknown to the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> for <hi>Cromwel</hi> had left him a true, ſober and warlike Nation. Our Seamen hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing curbed the <hi>Dutch,</hi> they defied (and that with Juſtice) all the Powers of the World to contend with them for the <hi>Empire</hi> of the Sea: We were Maſters of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> a very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Place, and which lying between the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> was, as we may ſay, a <hi>Throne</hi> upon which a King of <hi>England</hi> could decide, without Appeal, the Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> In ſhort, to crown all this, King <hi>Charles</hi> found the moſt liberal People that ever was. Now, after this, who will deny that <hi>England</hi> was then in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to reſtrain the <hi>French,</hi> and oblige them to ſtand ſtill, tho' they had bin in a much better poſture then they were: For theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions were not altogether appeaſed, and their Fleet, at that time, was ſo very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:39221:57"/>that they made but a very little fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure at Sea.</p>
            <p>By what has bin ſaid, I hope it appears, That if a Peace has not reigned in <hi>Europe</hi> ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, it is not becauſe there was not an <hi>Equilibrum</hi> ſet between <hi>France</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> but only becauſe thoſe whoſe gloriuos Province it was to maintain the <hi>publick Peace,</hi> were corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Men; and, therefore, I conclude, that if that Treaty be reſtor'd, if the Affairs of <hi>Eurpoe</hi> were reduc'd to the ſame Condition as they were then in, we ſhall enjoy a laſting Peace: For it is not to be ſuppoſed that any King of <hi>England</hi> for the future, will be perſuaded to ſell <hi>Dunkirk</hi> to the <hi>Franch;</hi> to teach them how to manage their Fleet; to join with them againſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> our <hi>Confederates;</hi> and, in a word, to ſuffer them to ſwallow <hi>Flanders,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Country. 'Tis ſaid, indeed, that Glory is the inſeparable Companion of Princes; but ſure I am, that the Prince we ſpeak of, muſt be excepted out of that Rule; for had he felt any ſting of that noble Paſſion, is it to be believ'd, that he would have diveſted himſelf of the moſt glorious Advantage and Title, that ever any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince enjoy'd, <hi>viz.</hi> of being the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpire</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the <hi>Defender</hi> of the <hi>Peace,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſince the Reſtitution of the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty is ſo abſolutely neceſſary for the Peace
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:39221:58"/>of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> 'tis plain, That <hi>England,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well as other Nations now in <hi>Confederacy</hi> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her, muſt be engag'd to continue the War ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we obtain it; but, beſides, we are engag'd by the Ties of Honour and Glory in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Quarrel. It hath been our ofrmer Princes Negligence, or our own, that hath made ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wide a Breach in <hi>Europe;</hi> and are we no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bound in <hi>Honour,</hi> as well as in <hi>Juſtice,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make it up? We have loſt the faireſt Flowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our Crown, in parting with the Advanta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ges I have mention'd; are we not bound therefore, for the Glory of our Country t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrive to regain them? <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> I know, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not yielded to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by the <hi>Pyrenea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Treaty; but was it not then our own, ſino<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoon after King <hi>Chrales</hi> ſold it?</p>
            <p>How much the loſs of <hi>Calais</hi> was bewail'd by our Fore-fathers, I think needleſs to te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my Reader, ſince it haſtened the death o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Queen <hi>Mary</hi> her ſelf; but with what Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility we ſuffer'd the loſs of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a Subject of Wonder; but I think it ſtill a grerter, to hear many People ſay, that it is againſt our Intereſt to demand the Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of that Place, unleſs they will ſay, that <hi>Calais</hi> was of more advantage to <hi>England,</hi> which I have no reaſon to believe, as I could eaſily ſhew, if I would break the Bounds which I have preſcrib'd to my ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:39221:58"/>
            <p>I would conclude here, and truly 'tis high time, but I think my ſelf oblig'd to anſwer, or at leaſt to prevent an Objection, which ſome People may poſſibly make. If almoſt all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> in <hi>Confederacy</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are ſcarce now able to reſiſt <hi>France,</hi> how is it poſſible that <hi>England</hi> along ſhould keep the <hi>Balance even</hi> between that Kingdom and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria?</hi> To this I anſwer, that if <hi>France</hi> was ſuppoſed to be always as pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, as it is at this day, or as it has been for many Years of late, the Objection would then hold good, and I ſhould reckon my ſelf ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worſe then a Fool to believe that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> would be able to <hi>counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balance</hi> it, ſince, as it is obſerv'd, ſo many States in conjunction together, find it a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult matter to do it; but if the <hi>French</hi> are once brought back to the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, and once ſhut up within theſe ancient Bounds, then I dare ſay, That <hi>England</hi> will be able to turn the Scale to what ſide ſoever ſhe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and eſpecially if <hi>Dunkirk</hi> be rreſtor'd to us. All the World knows, that the <hi>French</hi> have made great <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> and conſequently that they muſt be ſtronger then they were formerly; but the better to make this Truth ſenſible, and to give at the ſame time a juſt <hi>Idea</hi> of their <hi>preſent Strength,</hi> I'll offer to the Reader a Liſt of the principal Towns and Countries which they have acquir'd (to uſe their own Phraſe) ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:39221:59"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dunkirk</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bergue St. Vinox</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ypres</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Menin</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Furnes</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tournay</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lille</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Douay</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>St. Omer</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Valenciennes</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conde</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bouchain</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cambray</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aire</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>St. Guilain</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mons</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charleroy</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Namur</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Huy</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dinant</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charlemont</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maubeuge</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> with all its Dependencies</item>
               <item>The whole Dutchy of <hi>Lorrain</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The County of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> in which are very Conſiderable Places, as,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beſancon</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dole</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Salins,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Treves</hi> or <hi>Tryers,</hi> with almoſt that Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Montroial</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Strasbourgh</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philipsbourgh</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Landau</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Friburgh</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The whole Dutchy of <hi>Savoy</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Suſe</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cazal</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Niſſe</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ville Franche</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roſes,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity-ſake I ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All theſe Places are extraordinary well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and have large Dependencies, and this
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:39221:59"/>makes <hi>France</hi> ſo powerful, and almoſt impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrable either in <hi>Flanders</hi> or <hi>Germany;</hi> but it muſt be granted, that if the <hi>French</hi> were once oblig'd to reſtore them to their right Owners, they would ceaſe to be ſo formidable; from whence I conclude again, that it is in the <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renean</hi> Treaty alone, we can find that <hi>Equili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brium</hi> I have ſpoken of, and which is ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to the Peace of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:39221:60"/>
            <head>Books Printed for Richard Bladwin, <hi>at the</hi> Oxford-Arms <hi>in</hi> Warwick-Lane.</head>
            <p>A Poem on the late Promotions of ſeveral Eminent Perſons in Church and State by <hi>N. Tate,</hi> Servant to their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>Pleaſure with Profit: Conſiſting of Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of divers kinds, <hi>viz. Numerical, Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrical, Mechanical, Statical, Aſtronomical Horometrical, Cryptographical, Magnetical Automatical, Chymical</hi> and <hi>Hiſtorical.</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to recreate Ingenious Spirits; and to induce them to make farther ſcrutiny into theſe (and the like) Sublime Sciences. And to divert them from following ſuch Vices, to which Youth (in this Age) are ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd. By <hi>William Leybourn,</hi> Philomathes To this Work is alſo annext, a Treatiſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Algebra,</hi> according to the late Improvements applied to <hi>Numerical Queſtions,</hi> and <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try;</hi> with a New Series for the ſpeedy <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of Roots;</hi> as alſo a Converging Series
<pb facs="tcp:39221:60"/>for all manner of <hi>adſected Equations.</hi> By <hi>R. Sault,</hi> Maſter of the <hi>Mathematical School</hi> in <hi>Adam</hi>'s Court, in <hi>Broad-ſtreet,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Letters of State, written by Mr. <hi>John Milton,</hi> to moſt of the Sovereign Princes and Republicks of <hi>Europe,</hi> from the Year 1649. till the Year 1659. To which is added, An Account of his Life; together with ſeveral of his Poems; and a Catalogue of his Works, never, before Printed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bibliotheca Politica:</hi> Or, an Enquiry into the Ancient Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; with reſpect both to the juſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Regal Power, and to the Rights and Liberties of the Subject. Wherein all the chief Arguments as well againſt as for the Late Revolution, are impartially repreſented and conſidered, in XIII. Dialogues. Collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the beſt Authors both Ancient and Modern. To which is added, An Alphabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Index to the whole Work.</p>
            <p>The Works of <hi>Francis Rabelais,</hi> M. D. Or the Lives, Heroick Deeds and Sayings of <hi>Gargantua</hi> and <hi>Pantagruel;</hi> Done out of <hi>French</hi> by Sir <hi>Tho. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rchard,</hi> Kt. and others: With a large account of the Life and Works of the Author; particularly an Explanation of the moſt difficult Paſſages in them. Never before publiſh'd in any Language.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39221:61"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercury;</hi> or the Secret and Swift Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: Shewing how a Man may with Privacy and Speed communicate his Thoughts to a Friend at any diſtance. The Second Edition, by the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>John Wilkins,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> where are to be had, <hi>The World in the Moon,</hi> and <hi>Mathematical Magick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay concerning Obedience to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Powers, and the Duty of Subjects in all Revolutions: With ſome Conſiderations touching the preſent Juncture of Affairs.</p>
            <p>A Collection of Speeches of the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Henry</hi> lat Earl of <hi>Warrington,</hi> viz. I. His Speech upon his being Sworn Mayor of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> in <hi>November,</hi> 1691. II. His Speech to the Grand-Jury at <hi>Cheſter, April</hi> 13. 1692. III. His Charge to the Grand-Jury at the Quarter-Seſſions held for the County of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> on the 11th of <hi>October,</hi> 1692. IV. His Charge to the Grand-Jury at the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Seſſions, held for the County of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> on the 25th Day of <hi>April,</hi> 1693.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:39221:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
